<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter>
    <title>JMS</title>
    <sect1>
        <title>Introduction</title>
        <para>The JMS abstraction framework provided by spring consists of two different packages, jms and support.
        The org.springframework.jms package provides the core funtionality with implementations 
        of the JmsTemplate.  The support package contains utility classes for to obtain JMS destinations
        from JNDI and to create dynamic destinations.  
        </para>
        <para>
        There are two major releases of the JMS specification, 1.0.2 and 1.1.  JMS 1.0.2 defined two
        types of messaging domains, point-to-point and publish/subscribe.  The 1.0.2 API reflected these two
        messaging domains by providing a parallel class hierarcy for each domain.   Consequentially, a client 
        application was domain specific.  JMS 1.1 introduced the concept of domain unification that 
        minimized both the functional differences and client API differences between the two domains.        
        The JMS 1.1 specification is part of J2EE 1.4 and is required by EJB 2.1.  The JmsTemplate inteface
        was designed with domain unification in mind, so that it will be easy to transition from
        a JMS 1.0.2 to a 1.1 provider.        
        </para>
        <para>
        JMS functionality can be roughly divided into two areas, producing and consuming of messages.  In an
        J2EE environment, the ability to consume messages is provided for by MessageDriven beans while in a 
        stand-alone application this ability is provided for by the creation of MessageListeners or ConnectionConsumers.
        With a few small caveats, producing messages is similar in both a J2EE and stand-alone environment.
        </para>
        <!-- stand alone not good word to use.... -->
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Using the JmsTemplate</title>
        <para>
            Producing messgaes...Exception handling... other callbacks.
        </para>
        
        <para>
            Message <-> Bean converters.
        </para>
        
        <sect2>
          <title>Inside EJBs</title>
          <para>
          </para>
        </sect2>
        
        <sect2>
          <title>Outside EJBs</title>
          <para>
              The jms factory classes....  Standalone simple connectionfactory wrapper.
          </para>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
    
    <sect1>
        <title>Consuming messages</title>
        <para>
        </para>
        
        <sect2>
            <title>Message Driven Beans</title>
            <para>
                Getting the application context...
            </para>
        </sect2>
        
        <sect2>
            <title>MessageConsumers</title>
            <para>
                Factory classes....
            </para>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>

</chapter>
