<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<chapter id="part1"> 
  <title>Basic Application and Environment Setup</title>

  <para>This is a step-by-step account of how to develop a web application from scratch using the Spring Framework.</para>

  <para>Prerequisites:</para>

  <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
    <listitem>
      <para>Java SDK (We are currently using version 1.5)</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>Ant (using version 1.6.3)</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>Apache Tomcat (using version 5.5.17)</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para>You should also be reasonably comfortable using the above software.</para>
  <para>We are not going to cover a lot of background information or theory in this document -- there are plenty of books available that covers this in depth.
  Instead we will dive right into developing the application.</para>

  <section id="step1.1">
    <title>Development directory</title>

    <para>We are going to need a place to keep all the source and other files we will be creating, so we create a directory named 'springapp'. You can
    place this directory in your home folder or in some other location. We created ours in a 'Projects' directory that we already had in the home directory so 
    the path to our directory is now '$HOME/Projects/springapp'. Inside this directory we create a  sub-directory named 'src' to hold all Java source files. 
    Then we create another sub-directory that we name 'war'. This directory will hold everything that should go into the WAR file, that we would use to deploy 
    our application. All source files other than Java source, like JSPs and configuration files, belongs in this directory.</para>
    
  </section>
  
  <section id="step1.2">
        <title>index.jsp</title>
        <para>We will start by creating a JSP page named <emphasis>'index.jsp'</emphasis> in the war directory. This is the entry point for our application.</para>
        
        
  </section>
</chapter>

