<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="jdbc">
  <title>Data Access using JDBC</title>

  <sect1 id="jdbc-introduction">
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>The JDBC abstraction framework provided by Spring consists of four
    different packages <literal>core</literal>,
    <literal><literal>datasource</literal></literal>, <literal>object and
    <literal>support</literal></literal>.</para>

    <para>The <literal>org.springframework.jdbc.core</literal> package does as
    its name suggests contain the classes that provide the core functionality.
    This includes various SQLExceptionTranslator and
    DataFieldMaxValueIncrementer implementations as well as a DAO base class
    for JdbcTemplate usage.</para>

    <para>The <literal>org.springframework.jdbc.datasource</literal> package
    contains a utility class for easy DataSource access, and various simple
    DataSource implementations that can be used for testing and running
    unmodified JDBC code outside of a J2EE container. The utility class
    provides static methods to obtain connections from JNDI and to close
    connections if necessary. It has support for thread-bound connections,
    e.g. for use with DataSourceTransactionManager.</para>

    <para>Next, the <literal>org.springframework.jdbc.object</literal> package
    contains classes that represent RDBMS queries, updates, and stored
    procedures as threadsafe, reusable objects. This approach is modelled by
    JDO, although of course objects returned by queries are
    <quote>disconnected</quote> from the database. This higher level of JDBC
    abstraction depends on the lower-level abstraction in the
    <literal>org.springframework.jdbc.core</literal> package.</para>

    <para>Finally the <literal>org.springframework.jdbc.support</literal>
    package is where you find the <literal>SQLException</literal> transalation
    functionality and some utility classes.</para>

    <para>Exceptions thrown during JDBC processing are translated to
    exceptions defined in the <literal>org.springframework.dao</literal>
    package. This means that code using the Spring JDBC abstraction layer does
    not need to implement JDBC or RDBMS-specific error handling. All
    translated exceptions are unchecked giving you the option of catching the
    exceptions that you can recover from while allowing other exceptions to be
    propageted to the caller.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="jdbc-core">
    <title>Using the JDBC Core classes to control basic JDBC processing and
    error handling</title>

    <sect2 id="jdbc-JdbcTemplate">
      <title>JdbcTemplate</title>

      <para>This is the central class in the JDBC core package. It simplifies
      the use of JDBC since it handles the creation and release of resources.
      This helps to avoid common errors like forgetting to always close the
      connection. It executes the core JDBC workflow like statement creation
      and execution, leaving application code to provide SQL and extract
      results. This class executes SQL queries, update statments or stored
      procedure calls, initating iteration over ResultSets and extraction of
      returned parameter values. It also catches JDBC exceptions and
      translates them to the generic, more informative, exception hierarchy
      defined in the <literal>org.springframework.dao</literal>
      package.</para>

      <para>Code using this class only need to implement callback interfaces,
      giving them a clearly defined contract. The
      <literal>PreparedStatementCreator</literal> callback interface creates a
      prepared statement given a Connection provided by this class, providing
      SQL and any necessary parameters. The same is true for the
      <literal>CallableStatementCreateor</literal> interface which creates
      callable statement. The <literal>RowCallbackHandler</literal> interface
      extracts values from each row of a ResultSet.</para>

      <para>This class can be used within a service implementation via direct
      instantiation with a DataSource reference, or get prepared in an
      application context and given to services as bean reference. Note: The
      DataSource should always be configured as a bean in the application
      context, in the first case given to the service directly, in the second
      case to the prepared template. Because this class is parameterizable by
      the callback interfaces and the SQLExceptionTranslator interface, it
      isn't necessary to subclass it. All SQL issued by this class is
      logged.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>DataSource</title>

      <para>In order to work with data from a database, we need to obtain a
      connection to the database. The way Spring does this is through a
      <literal>DataSource</literal>. A <literal>DataSource</literal> is part
      of the JDBC specification and can be seen as a generalized connection
      factory. It allows a container or a framework to hide connection pooling
      and transaction management issues from the application code. As a
      developer, you don't need to know any details about how to connect to
      the database, that is the responibility for the administrator that sets
      up the datasource. You will most likely have to fulfil both roles while
      you are developing and testing you code though, but you will not
      necessarily have to know how the production data source is
      configured.</para>

      <para>When using Spring's JDBC layer, you can either obtain a data
      source from JNDI or you can configure your own, using an implementation
      that is provided in the Spring distribution. The latter comes in handy
      for unit testing outside of a web container. We will use the
      <literal>DriverManagerDataSource</literal> implementation for this
      section but there are several additional implementations that will be
      covered later on. The <literal>DriverManagerDataSource</literal> works
      the same way that you probably are used to work when you obtain a JDBC
      connection. You have to specify the fully qualified class name of the
      JDBC driver that you are using so that the
      <literal>DriverManager</literal> can load the driver class. Then you
      have to provide a url that varies between JDBC drivers. You have to
      consult the documentation for your driver for the correct value to use
      here. Finally you must provide a username and a password that will be
      used to connect to the database. Here is an example of how to configure
      a <literal>DriverManagerDataSource:</literal></para>

      <programlisting>DriverManagerDataSource dataSource = new DriverManagerDataSource();
dataSource.setDriverClassName( "org.hsqldb.jdbcDriver");
dataSource.setUrl( "jdbc:hsqldb:hsql://localhost:");
dataSource.setUsername( "sa");
dataSource.setPassword( ""); </programlisting>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="jdbc-SQLExceptionTranslator">
      <title>SQLExceptionTranslator</title>

      <para><literal>SQLExceptionTranslator</literal> is an interface to be
      implemented by classes that can translate between SQLExceptions and our
      data access strategy-agnostic
      <literal>org.springframework.dao.DataAccessException</literal>.</para>

      <para>Implementations can be generic (for example, using SQLState codes
      for JDBC) or proprietary (for example, using Oracle error codes) for
      greater precision.</para>

      <para><literal>SQLErrorCodeSQLExceptionTranslator</literal> is the
      implementation of SQLExceptionTranslator that is used by default. This
      implementation uses specific vendor codes. More precise than
      <literal>SQLState</literal> implementation, but vendor specific. The
      error code translations are based on codes held in a JavaBean type class
      named <literal>SQLErrorCodes</literal>. This class is created and
      populated by an <literal>SQLErrorCodesFactory</literal> which as the
      name suggests is a factory for creating <literal>SQLErrorCodes</literal>
      based on the contents of a configuration file named
      "sql-error-codes.xml". This file is populated with vendor codes and
      based on the DatabaseProductName taken from the DatabaseMetaData, the
      codes for the current database are used.</para>

      <para>The <literal>SQLErrorCodeSQLExceptionTranslator</literal> applies
      the following matching rules:<itemizedlist spacing="compact">
          <listitem>
            <para>Try custom translation implemented by any subclass. Note
            that this class is concrete and is typically used itself, in which
            case this rule doesn't apply.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Apply error code matching. Error codes are obtained from the
            SQLErrorCodesFactory by default. This looks up error codes from
            the classpath and keys into them from the database name from the
            database metadata.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Use the fallback translator. SQLStateSQLExceptionTranslator
            is the default fallback translator.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist></para>

      <para><literal>SQLErrorCodeSQLExceptionTranslator</literal> can be
      extended the following way: <programlisting format="linespecific"
      xml:space="preserve">public class MySQLErrorCodesTransalator extends SQLErrorCodeSQLExceptionTranslator {
  protected DataAccessException customTranslate(String task, String sql, SQLException sqlex) {
    if (sqlex.getErrorCode() == -12345)
      return new DeadlockLoserDataAccessException(task, sqlex);
    return null;
  }
}</programlisting>In this example the specific error code '-12345' is
      translated and any other errors are simply left to be translated by the
      default translator implementation. To use this custom translator, it is
      necessary to pass it to the <literal>JdbcTemplate</literal> using the
      method <literal>setExceptionTranslator</literal> and to use this
      <literal>JdbcTemplate</literal> for all of the data access processing
      where this translator is needed. Here is an example of how this custom
      translator can be used: <programlisting format="linespecific"
      xml:space="preserve">// create a JdbcTemplate and set data source 
JdbcTemplate jt = new JdbcTemplate(); 
jt.setDataSource(dataSource); 
// create a custom translator and set the datasource for the default translation lookup 
MySQLErrorCodesTransalator tr = new MySQLErrorCodesTransalator(); 
tr.setDataSource(dataSource); 
jt.setExceptionTranslator(tr); 
// use the JdbcTemplate for this SqlUpdate 
SqlUpdate su = new SqlUpdate(); 
su.setJdbcTemplate(jt); 
su.setSql("update orders set shipping_charge = shipping_charge * 1.05"); 
su.compile(); 
su.update();</programlisting>The custom translator is passed a data source
      because we still want the default translation to look up the error codes
      in <literal>sql-error-codes.xml</literal>.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Executing Statements</title>

      <para>To execute an SQL statement, there is very little code needed. All
      you need is a <literal>DataSource</literal> and a
      <literal>JdbcTemplate</literal>. Once you have that, you can use a
      number of convenience methods that are provided with the
      <literal>JdbcTemplate</literal>. Here is a short example showing what
      you need to include for a minimal but fully functional class that
      creates a new table.<programlisting>import javax.sql.DataSource;
import org.springframework.jdbc.core.JdbcTemplate;

/**
 * @author trisberg
 */
public class ExecuteAStatement {
  private JdbcTemplate jt;
  private DataSource dataSource;

  public void doExecute() {
    jt = new JdbcTemplate(dataSource);
    jt.execute("create table mytable (id integer, name varchar(100))"); 
  }

  public void setDataSource(DataSource dataSource) {
    this.dataSource = dataSource;
  }
}</programlisting></para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Running Queries</title>

      <para>In addition to the execute methods, there is a large number of
      query methods. Some of these methods are intended to be used for queries
      that return a single value. Maybe you want to retrieve a count or a
      specific value from one row. If that is the case then you can use
      <literal>queryForInt</literal>,<literal>queryForLong</literal> or
      <literal>queryForObject</literal>. The latter will convert the returned
      JDBC Type to the Java class that is passed in as an argument. If the
      type conversion is invalid, then an
      <literal>InvalidDataAccessApiUsageException</literal> will be thrown.
      Here is an example that contains two query methods, one for an
      <literal>int</literal> and one that queries for a
      <literal>String</literal>.</para>

      <programlisting>import javax.sql.DataSource;
import org.springframework.jdbc.core.JdbcTemplate;

/**
 * @author trisberg
 */
public class RunAQuery {
  private JdbcTemplate jt;
  private DataSource dataSource;
  
  public int getCount() {
    jt = new JdbcTemplate(dataSource);
    int count = jt.queryForInt("select count(*) from mytable");
    return count;
  }

  public String getName() {
    jt = new JdbcTemplate(dataSource);
    String name = (String) jt.queryForObject("select name from mytable", java.lang.String.class);
    return name;
  }

  public void setDataSource(DataSource dataSource) {
    this.dataSource = dataSource;
  }
}</programlisting>

      <para>In addition to the singe results query methods there are several
      methods that return a List with an entry for each row that the query
      returned. The most generic one is <literal>queryForList</literal> which
      returns a <literal>List</literal> where each entry is a
      <literal>Map</literal> with each entry in the map representing the
      column value for that row. If we add a method to the above example to
      retrieve a list of all the rows, it would look like this:</para>

      <programlisting>  public List getList() {
    jt = new JdbcTemplate(dataSource);
    List rows = jt.queryForList("select * from mytable");
    return rows;
  }</programlisting>

      <para>The list returned would look something like this:
      <literal>[{name=Bob, id=1}, {name=Mary, id=2}].</literal></para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Updating the database</title>

      <para>ToDo</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="jdbc-datasource">
    <title>Controling how we connect to the database</title>

    <sect2 id="jdbc-DataSourceUtils">
      <title>DataSourceUtils</title>

      <para>Helper class that provides static methods to obtain connections
      from JNDI and close connections if necessary. Has support for
      thread-bound connections, e.g. for use with
      DataSourceTransactionManager.</para>

      <para>Note: The getDataSourceFromJndi methods are targetted at
      applications that do not use a BeanFactory resp. an ApplicationContext.
      With the latter, it is preferable to preconfigure your beans or even
      <literal><literal>JdbcTemplate</literal></literal> instances in the
      factory: <literal>JndiObjectFactoryBean</literal> can be used to fetch a
      <literal><literal>DataSource</literal></literal> from JNDI and give the
      <literal><literal>DataSource</literal></literal> bean reference to other
      beans. Switching to another
      <literal><literal>DataSource</literal></literal> is just a matter of
      configuration then: You can even replace the definition of the
      <literal>FactoryBean</literal> with a non-JNDI
      <literal><literal>DataSource</literal></literal>!</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="jdbc-SmartDataSource">
      <title>SmartDataSource</title>

      <para>Interface to be implemented by classes that can provide a
      connection to a relational database. Extends the
      <literal>javax.sql.DataSource</literal> interface to allow classes using
      it to query whether or not the connection should be closed after a given
      operation. This can sometimes be useful for efficiency, if we know that
      we want to reuse a connection.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="jdbc-AbstractDataSource">
      <title>AbstractDataSource</title>

      <para>Abstract base class for Spring's <literal>DataSource</literal>
      implementations, taking care of the "uninteresting" glue. This is the
      class you would extend if you are writing your own
      <literal>DataSource</literal> implementation.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="jdbc-SingleConnectionDataSource">
      <title>SingleConnectionDataSource</title>

      <para>Implementation of <literal>SmartDataSource</literal> that wraps a
      single connection which is not closed after use. Obviously, this is not
      multi-threading capable.</para>

      <para>If client code will call close in the assumption of a pooled
      connection, like when using persistence tools, set
      <literal>suppressClose</literal> to true. This will return a
      close-suppressing proxy instead of the physical connection. Be aware
      that you will not be able to cast this to a native Oracle Connection or
      the like anymore.</para>

      <para>This is primarily a test class. For example, it enables easy
      testing of code outside an application server, in conjunction with a
      simple JNDI environment. In contrast to
      <literal>DriverManagerDataSource</literal>, it reuses the same
      connection all the time, avoiding excessive creation of physical
      connections.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="jdbc-DriverManagerDataSource">
      <title>DriverManagerDataSource</title>

      <para>Implementation of <literal>SmartDataSource</literal> that
      configures a plain old JDBC Driver via bean properties, and returns a
      new connection every time.</para>

      <para>Useful for test or standalone environments outside of a J2EE
      container, either as a <literal>DataSource</literal> bean in a
      respective ApplicationContext, or in conjunction with a simple JNDI
      environment. Pool-assuming <literal>Connection.close()</literal> calls
      will simply close the connection, so any DataSource-aware persistence
      code should work.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="jdbc-DataSourceTransactionManager">
      <title>DataSourceTransactionManager</title>

      <para>PlatformTransactionManager implementation for single JDBC data
      sources. Binds a JDBC connection from the specified data source to the
      thread, potentially allowing for one thread connection per data
      source.</para>

      <para>Application code is required to retrieve the JDBC connection via
      <literal>DataSourceUtils.getConnection(DataSource)</literal> instead of
      J2EE's standard <literal>DataSource.getConnection</literal>. This is
      recommended anyway, as it throws unchecked
      <literal>org.springframework.dao</literal> exceptions instead of checked
      <literal>SQLException</literal>. All framework classes like
      <literal>JdbcTemplate</literal> use this strategy implicitly. If not
      used with this transaction manager, the lookup strategy behaves exactly
      like the common one - it can thus be used in any case.</para>

      <para>Supports custom isolation levels, and timeouts that get applied as
      appropriate JDBC statement query timeouts. To support the latter,
      application code must either use <literal>JdbcTemplate</literal> or call
      <literal>DataSourceUtils.<literal>applyTransactionTimeout</literal></literal>
      method for each created statement.</para>

      <para>This implementation can be used instead of
      <literal>JtaTransactionManager</literal> in the single resource case, as
      it does not require the container to support JTA. Switching between both
      is just a matter of configuration, if you stick to the required
      connection lookup pattern. Note that JTA does not support custom
      isolation levels!</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="jdbc-object">
    <title>Modeling JDBC operations as Java objects</title>

    <para>The <literal>org.springframework.jdbc.object</literal> package
    contains the classes that allow you to access the database in a more
    object oriented manner. You can execute queries and get the results back
    as a list containing business objects with the relational column data
    mapped to the properties of the business obejct. You can also execute
    stored procedures and run update, delete and insert statemente.</para>

    <sect2 id="jdbc-SqlQuery">
      <title>SqlQuery</title>

      <para>Reusable threadsafe object to represent an SQL query. Subclasses
      must implement the newResultReader() method to provide an object that
      can save the results while iterating over the ResultSet. This class is
      rarely used directly since the <literal>MappingSqlQuery</literal>, that
      extends this class, provides a much more covenient inplementation for
      mapping rows to java classes. Other implementations that extend
      <literal>SqlQuery</literal> are
      <literal>MappingSqlQueryWithParameters</literal> and
      <literal>UpdatableSqlQuery</literal>.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="jdbc-MappingSqlQuery">
      <title>MappingSqlQuery</title>

      <para><literal>MappingSqlQuery</literal> is a reusable query in which
      concrete subclasses must implement the abstract
      <literal>mapRow(ResultSet, int)</literal> method to convert each row of
      the JDBC <literal>ResultSet</literal> into an object.</para>

      <para>Of all the <literal>SqlQuery</literal> implementations, this is
      the one used most often and it is also the one that is the easiest to
      use.</para>

      <para>Here is a brief example of a custom query that maps the data from
      the customer table to a Java object called Customer.</para>

      <programlisting>  private class CustomerMappingQuery extends MappingSqlQuery {
    public CustomerMappingQuery(DataSource ds) {
      super(ds, "SELECT id, name FROM customer WHERE id = ?");
      super.declareParameter(new SqlParameter("id", Types.INTEGER));
      compile();
    }
    public Object mapRow(ResultSet rs, int rowNumber) throws SQLException {
      Customer cust = new Customer();
      cust.setId((Integer) rs.getObject("id"));
      cust.setName(rs.getString("name"));
      return cust;
    } 
  }</programlisting>

      <para>We provide a constructor for this customer query that takes the
      <literal>DataSource</literal> as the only parameter. In this constructor
      we call the constructor on the superclass with the
      <literal>DataSource</literal> and the SQL that should be executed to
      retrieve the rows for this query. This SQL will be used to create a
      <literal>PreparedStatement</literal> so it may contain placeholders for
      any parameters to be passed in during execution. Each parameter must be
      declared using the <literal>declareParameter</literal> method passing in
      an <literal>SqlParameter</literal>. The <literal>SqlParameter</literal>
      takes a name and the JDBC type as defined in
      <literal>java.sql.Types</literal>. After all paramaters have been
      defined we call the <literal>compile</literal> method so the statement
      can be prepared and later be executed.</para>

      <para>Let's take a look at the code where this custom query is
      instantiated and executed:</para>

      <programlisting>  public Customer getCustomer(Integer id) {
    CustomerMappingQuery custQry = new CustomerMappingQuery(dataSource); 
    Object[] parms = new Object[1];
    parms[0] = id;
    List customers = custQry.execute(parms);
    if (customers.size() &gt; 0)
      return (Customer) customers.get(0);
    else
      return null;
  }</programlisting>

      <para>The method in this example retrieves the customer with the id that
      is passed in as the only parameter. After creating an instance of the
      <literal>CustomerMappingQuery</literal> class we create an array of
      objects that will contain all parameters that are passed in. In this
      case there is only one parameter and it is passed in as an
      <literal>Integer</literal>. Now we are ready to execute the query using
      this array of parameters and we get a <literal>List</literal> that
      contains a <literal>Customer</literal> object for each row that was
      returned for our query. In this case it will only be one entry if there
      was a match.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="jdbc-SqlUpdate">
      <title>SqlUpdate</title>

      <para>RdbmsOperation subclass representing a SQL update. Like a query,
      an update object is reusable. Like all RdbmsOperation objects, an update
      can have parameters and is defined in SQL.</para>

      <para>This class provides a number of update() methods analogous to the
      execute() methods of query objects.</para>

      <para>This class is concrete. Although it can be subclassed (for example
      to add a custom update method) it can easily be parameterized by setting
      SQL and declaring parameters.</para>

      <para>Example - ToDo</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="jdbc-StoredProcedure">
      <title>StoredProcedure</title>

      <para>Superclass for object abstractions of RDBMS stored procedures.
      This class is abstract and its execute methods are protected, preventing
      use other than through a subclass that offers tighter typing.</para>

      <para>The inherited sql property is the name of the stored procedure in
      the RDBMS. Note that JDBC 3.0 introduces named parameters, although the
      other features provided by this class are still necessary in JDBC
      3.0.</para>

      <para>Example - ToDo</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="jdbc-SqlFunction">
      <title>SqlFunction</title>

      <para>SQL "function" wrapper for a query that returns a single row of
      results. The default behavior is to return an int, but that can be
      overridden by using the methods with an extra return type parameter.
      This is similar to using the <literal>queryForXxx</literal> methods of
      the <literal>JdbcTemplate</literal>. The advantage with
      <literal>SqlFunction</literal> is that you don't have to create the
      <literal>JdbcTemplate</literal>, it is done behind the scenes.</para>

      <para>This class is intended to use to call SQL functions that return a
      single result using a query like "select user()" or "select sysdate from
      dual". It is not intended for calling more complex stored functions or
      for using a <literal>CallableStatement</literal> to invoke a stored
      procedure or stored function. Use <literal>StoredProcedure</literal> or
      <literal>SqlCall</literal> for this type of processing.</para>

      <para>This is a concrete class, which there is normally no need to
      subclass. Code using this package can create an object of this type,
      declaring SQL and parameters, and then invoke the appropriate run method
      repeatedly to execute the function. Here is an example of retrieving the
      count of rows from a table:</para>

      <para><programlisting>  public int countRows() {
    SqlFunction sf = new SqlFunction(dataSource, "select count(*) from mytable");
    sf.compile();
    return sf.run();
  }</programlisting></para>

      <para></para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
</chapter>