<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<chapter id="jdbc">
	<title>Data access using JDBC</title>
	<section id="jdbc-introduction">
		<title>Introduction</title>
		<para>
			The value-add provided by Spring's JDBC abstraction framework is perhaps
			best shown by the following list (note that only the italicized lines
			need to be coded by an application developer when using Spring's JDBC
			abstraction framework):
		</para>
		<orderedlist numeration="arabic">
			<listitem>
				<para>Define connection parameters</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Open the connection</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para><emphasis>Specify the statement</emphasis></para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Prepare and execute the statement</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Set up the loop to iterate through the results (if any)</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para><emphasis>Do the work for each iteration</emphasis></para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Process any exception</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Handle transactions</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Close the connection</para>
			</listitem>
		</orderedlist>
		<para>
			Spring takes care of all the grungy, low-level details that can make
			JDBC such a tedious API to develop against.
		</para>
		<section>
			<title>The package hierarchy</title>
			<para>
				The JDBC abstraction framework provided by Spring consists of four
				different packages <literal>core</literal>, <literal>dataSource</literal>,
				<literal>object</literal>, and <literal>support</literal>.
			</para>
			<para>
				The <literal>org.springframework.jdbc.core</literal> package
				contains the <classname>JdbcTemplate</classname> class and its various 
				callback interfaces, plus a variety of related classes.
			</para>
			<para>
				The <literal>org.springframework.jdbc.datasource</literal> package
				contains a utility class for easy <interfacename>DataSource</interfacename>
				access, and various simple <interfacename>DataSource</interfacename>
				implementations that can be used for testing and running
				unmodified JDBC code outside of a J2EE container. The utility class
				provides static methods to obtain connections from JNDI and to close
				connections if necessary. It has support for thread-bound connections,
				e.g. for use with <classname>DataSourceTransactionManager</classname>.
			</para>
			<para>
				Next, the <literal>org.springframework.jdbc.object</literal> package
				contains classes that represent RDBMS queries, updates, and stored
				procedures as thread safe, reusable objects. This approach is modeled by
				JDO, although of course objects returned by queries are
				<quote>disconnected</quote> from the database. This higher level of JDBC
				abstraction depends on the lower-level abstraction in the
				<literal>org.springframework.jdbc.core</literal> package.
			</para>
			<para>
				Finally the <literal>org.springframework.jdbc.support</literal>
				package is where you find the <classname>SQLException</classname> translation
				functionality and some utility classes.
			</para>
			<para>
				Exceptions thrown during JDBC processing are translated to
				exceptions defined in the <literal>org.springframework.dao</literal>
				package. This means that code using the Spring JDBC abstraction layer does
				not need to implement JDBC or RDBMS-specific error handling. All
				translated exceptions are unchecked giving you the option of catching the
				exceptions that you can recover from while allowing other exceptions to be
				propagated to the caller.
			</para>
		</section>
	</section>
	<section id="jdbc-core">
		<title>Using the JDBC Core classes to control basic JDBC processing and error handling</title>
		<section id="jdbc-JdbcTemplate">
			<title><classname>JdbcTemplate</classname></title>
			<para>
				The <classname>JdbcTemplate</classname> class is the central class in
				the JDBC core package. It simplifies the use of JDBC since it handles the
				creation and release of resources. This helps to avoid common errors such
				as forgetting to always close the connection. It executes the core JDBC
				workflow like statement creation and execution, leaving application code
				to provide SQL and extract results. This class executes SQL queries, update
				statements or stored procedure calls, imitating iteration over
				<interfacename>ResultSet</interfacename>s and extraction of returned
				parameter values. It also catches JDBC exceptions and
				translates them to the generic, more informative, exception hierarchy
				defined in the <literal>org.springframework.dao</literal> package.
			</para>
			<para>
				Code using this class only need to implement callback interfaces,
				giving them a clearly defined contract. The
				<interfacename>PreparedStatementCreator</interfacename> callback
				interface creates a	prepared statement given a
				<interfacename>Connection</interfacename> provided by this class,
				providing SQL and any necessary parameters. The same is true for the
				<interfacename>CallableStatementCreator</interfacename> interface
				which creates callable statement. The
				<interfacename>RowCallbackHandler</interfacename> interface extracts
				values from each row of a <interfacename>ResultSet</interfacename>.
			</para>
			<para>
				This class can be used within a service implementation via direct
				instantiation with a <interfacename>DataSource</interfacename> reference,
				or get prepared in an application context and given to services as a
				bean reference. Note: the <interfacename>DataSource</interfacename> should
				always be configured as a bean in the application context, in the first
				case given to the service directly, in the second case to the prepared
				template. Because this class is parameterizable by the callback interfaces
				and the <interfacename>SQLExceptionTranslator</interfacename> interface, it
				isn't necessary to subclass it.
			</para>
			<para>
				Finally, please be aware that all of the SQL issued by this class is logged
				at the <literal>'DEBUG'</literal> level under the category corresponding
				to the fully qualified class name of the template instance (typically
				<classname>JdbcTemplate</classname>, but it may be different if a custom
				subclass of the <classname>JdbcTemplate</classname> class is being used).
			</para>
		</section>
		<section id="jdbc-NamedParameterJdbcTemplate">
			<title><classname>NamedParameterJdbcTemplate</classname></title>
			<para>
				The <classname>NamedParameterJdbcTemplate</classname> class adds support
				for programming JDBC statements using named parameters (as opposed to
				programming JDBC statements using only classic placeholder
				(<literal>'?'</literal>) arguments.
			</para>
			<para>
				The <classname>NamedParameterJdbcTemplate</classname> class wraps
				a vanilla <classname>JdbcTemplate</classname>, and delegates to the
				wrapped <classname>JdbcTemplate</classname> to do much of its work.
				This section will describe only those areas of the
				<classname>NamedParameterJdbcTemplate</classname> class that differ from
				the <classname>JdbcTemplate</classname> itself; namely, programming
				JDBC statements using named parameters.
			</para>
			<para>
				The expect usage pattern for the <classname>NamedParameterJdbcTemplate</classname>
				class is perhaps best illustrated by looking at an example (the finer
				points will be addressed immediately thereafter).
			</para>
			<programlisting><lineannotation>// some JDBC-backed DAO class...</lineannotation><![CDATA[
public int countOfActorsByFirstName(String firstName) {

    String sql = "select count(0) from T_ACTOR where first_name = :first_name";

    NamedParameterJdbcTemplate template = new NamedParameterJdbcTemplate(this.getDataSource());
    SqlParameterSource namedParameters = new SimpleSqlParameterSource("first_name", firstName);

    return template.queryForInt(sql, namedParameters);
}]]></programlisting>
			<para>
				Notice the use of the named parameter notation in the value assigned
				to the <literal>'sql'</literal> variable, and the corresponding value
				that is plugged into the <literal>'namedParameters'</literal> variable
				(of type <classname>SimpleSqlParameterSource</classname>).
			</para>
			<para>
				If you like, you can also pass along named parameters (and their
				corresponding values) to a <classname>NamedParameterJdbcTemplate</classname>
				instance using the (perhaps more familiar)
				<interfacename>Map</interfacename>-based style.
				(The rest of the methods exposed by the
				<interfacename>NamedParameterJdbcOperations</interfacename> - and implemented by the <classname>NamedParameterJdbcTemplate</classname> class)
				follow a similar pattern and will not be covered here.)
			</para>
<programlisting><lineannotation>// some JDBC-backed DAO class...</lineannotation><![CDATA[
public int countOfActorsByFirstName(String firstName) {

    String sql = "select count(0) from T_ACTOR where first_name = :first_name";

    NamedParameterJdbcTemplate template = new NamedParameterJdbcTemplate(this.getDataSource());
    Map namedParameters = new HashMap();
    namedParameters.put("first_name", firstName);

    return template.queryForInt(sql, namedParameters);
}]]></programlisting>
			<para>
				Another nice feature related to the <classname>NamedParameterJdbcTemplate</classname>
				(and existing in the same Java package) is the <interfacename>SqlParameterSource</interfacename>
				interface. You have already seen an example of an implementation of this
				interface in one of the preceding code snippets (the
				<classname>SimpleSqlParameterSource</classname> class). The entire
				point of the <interfacename>SqlParameterSource</interfacename> is to serve as
				a source of named parameter values to a <classname>NamedParameterJdbcTemplate</classname>.
				The <classname>SimpleSqlParameterSource</classname> class is (as the name implies)
				a very simple implementation, that is simply an adapter around a
				<interfacename>java.util.Map</interfacename>, and its use (should) be
				self-evident (if it is not then do raise a JIRA issue asking for more
				documentation in this regard).
			</para>
			<para>
				Another, more interesting, implementation of the
				<interfacename>SqlParameterSource</interfacename> interface is the
				<classname>BeanPropertySqlParameterSource</classname> class. This
				class wraps an arbitrary JavaBean-like object, and uses the properties
				of the wrapped object as the source of named parameter values. An
				example will perhaps make its use clear.
			</para>
			<programlisting><lineannotation>// some JavaBean-like class...</lineannotation><![CDATA[
public class Actor {

    private Long id;
    private String firstName;
    private String lastName;
    
    public String getFirstName() {
        return this.firstName;
    }
    
    public String getLastName() {
        return this.lastName;
    }
    
    public Long getId() {
        return this.id;
    }
    
    ]]><lineannotation>// setters omitted...</lineannotation><![CDATA[

}]]></programlisting>
			<programlisting><lineannotation>// some JDBC-backed DAO class...</lineannotation><![CDATA[
public int countOfActors(Actor exampleActor) {

	]]><lineannotation>// notice how the named parameters match the properties of the above 'Actor' class</lineannotation><![CDATA[
    String sql = "select count(0) from T_ACTOR where first_name = :firstName and last_name = :lastName";

    NamedParameterJdbcTemplate template = new NamedParameterJdbcTemplate(this.getDataSource());
    SqlParameterSource namedParameters = new BeanPropertySqlParameterSource(exampleActor);

    return template.queryForInt(sql, namedParameters);
}]]></programlisting>
			<para>
				Remember that the <classname>NamedParameterJdbcTemplate</classname> class
				<emphasis>wraps</emphasis> a classic <classname>JdbcTemplate</classname>
				template... if you need access to the wrapped
				<classname>JdbcTemplate</classname> instance (to access some of the
				functionality only present in the <classname>JdbcTemplate</classname>
				class), then you can use the <literal>getJdbcOperations()</literal>
				method to access the wrapped <classname>JdbcTemplate</classname>
				<emphasis>via the <interfacename>JdbcOperations</interfacename>
				interface</emphasis>.
			</para>
			<para>
				The <classname>NamedParameterJdbcTemplate</classname> class is threadsafe,
				and the expected usage pattern is not to instantiate a new
				<classname>NamedParameterJdbcTemplate</classname> instance per operation, but
				rather to simply configure a single <classname>NamedParameterJdbcTemplate</classname>
				instance per <interfacename>DataSource</interfacename> (typically via a Spring
				IoC container if you are using Spring's IoC technology) and then share
				that same instance amongst those DAOs (typically) that need it.
			</para>
		</section>
		<section id="jdbc-SimpleJdbcTemplate">
			<title><classname>SimpleJdbcTemplate</classname></title>
			<note>
				<para>
					<emphasis>Please be aware that the functionality offered by this class is
					only available to you if you are using Java 5 (Tiger).</emphasis>
				</para>
			</note>
			<para>
				The <classname>SimpleJdbcTemplate</classname> class is a wrapper around
				the classic Spring <classname>JdbcTemplate</classname>, that takes advantage
				of Java 5 language features such as varargs and autoboxing. The
				<classname>SimpleJdbcTemplate</classname> class is somewhat of a sop
				to the syntactic-sugar-like features of Java 5, but as anyone who has
				developed on Java 5 and then had to move back to developing on a
				previous version of the JDK will know, those syntactic-sugar-like features
				sure are nice.
			</para>
			<para>
				The value-add of the <classname>SimpleJdbcTemplate</classname> class
				in the area of syntactic-sugar is definitely best illustrated with a
				<emphasis>'before and after'</emphasis> example. The following code
				snippet shows first some data access code using the classic Spring
				<classname>JdbcTemplate</classname>, followed immediately thereafter
				by a code snippet that does the same job, only this time using the
				<classname>SimpleJdbcTemplate</classname>.
			</para>
			<programlisting><lineannotation>// classic <classname>JdbcTemplate</classname>-style...</lineannotation><![CDATA[
public Actor findActor(long id) {
    String sql = "select id, first_name, last_name from T_ACTOR where id = ?";
    
    RowMapper mapper = new RowMapper() {
    
        public Object mapRow(ResultSet rs, int rowNum) throws SQLException {
            Actor actor = new Actor();
            actor.setId(rs.getLong(Long.valueOf(rs.getLong("id"))));
            actor.setFirstName(rs.getString("first_name"));
            actor.setLastName(rs.getString("last_name"));
            return actor;
        }
    };
    
    ]]><lineannotation>// normally this would be dependency injected of course...</lineannotation><![CDATA[
    JdbcTemplate jdbcTemplate = new JdbcTemplate(this.getDataSource());
    
    ]]><lineannotation>// notice the cast, and the wrapping up of the 'id' argument
    // in an array, and the boxing of the 'id' argument as a reference type</lineannotation><![CDATA[
    return (Actor) jdbcTemplate.queryForObject(sql, mapper, new Object[] {Long.valueOf(id)});
}]]></programlisting>
			<para>
				Here is the same method, only this time using the
				<classname>SimpleJdbcTemplate</classname>; notice how much 'cleaner'
				the code is.
			</para>
			<programlisting><lineannotation>// <classname>SimpleJdbcTemplate</classname>-style...</lineannotation><![CDATA[
public Actor findActor(long id) {
    String sql = "select id, first_name, last_name from T_ACTOR where id = ?";

    ParameterizedRowMapper<Actor> mapper = new ParameterizedRowMapper()<Actor> {
    
        ]]><lineannotation>// notice the return type (c.f. Java 5 covariant return types)</lineannotation><![CDATA[
        public Actor mapRow(ResultSet rs, int rowNum) throws SQLException {
            Actor actor = new Actor();
            actor.setId(rs.getLong("id"));
            actor.setFirstName(rs.getString("first_name"));
            actor.setLastName(rs.getString("last_name"));
            return actor;
        }
    };

    ]]><lineannotation>// again, normally this would be dependency injected of course...</lineannotation><![CDATA[
    SimpleJdbcTemplate simpleJdbcTemplate = new SimpleJdbcTemplate(this.getDataSource());

    return simpleJdbcTemplate.queryForObject(sql, mapper, id);
}]]></programlisting>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title><interfacename>DataSource</interfacename></title>
			<para>
				In order to work with data from a database, one needs to obtain a
				connection to the database. The way Spring does this is through a
				<interfacename>DataSource</interfacename>. A
				<interfacename>DataSource</interfacename> is part
				of the JDBC specification and can be seen as a generalized connection
				factory. It allows a container or a framework to hide connection pooling
				and transaction management issues from the application code. As a
				developer, you don't need to know any details about how to connect to
				the database, that is the responsibility for the administrator that sets
				up the datasource. You will most likely have to fulfill both roles while
				you are developing and testing you code though, but you will not
				necessarily have to know how the production data source is
				configured.
			</para>
			<para>
				When using Spring's JDBC layer, you can either obtain a data
				source from JNDI or you can configure your own, using an implementation
				that is provided in the Spring distribution. The latter comes in handy
				for unit testing outside of a web container. We will use the
				<classname>DriverManagerDataSource</classname> implementation for this
				section but there are several additional implementations that will be
				covered later on. The <classname>DriverManagerDataSource</classname> works
				the same way that you probably are used to work when you obtain a JDBC
				connection. You have to specify the fully qualified class name of the
				JDBC driver that you are using so that the
				<classname>DriverManager</classname> can load the driver class. Then you
				have to provide a url that varies between JDBC drivers. You have to
				consult the documentation for your driver for the correct value to use
				here. Finally you must provide a username and a password that will be
				used to connect to the database. Here is an example of how to configure
				a <classname>DriverManagerDataSource</classname>:
			</para>
			<programlisting><![CDATA[DriverManagerDataSource dataSource = new DriverManagerDataSource();
dataSource.setDriverClassName("org.hsqldb.jdbcDriver");
dataSource.setUrl("jdbc:hsqldb:hsql://localhost:");
dataSource.setUsername("sa");
dataSource.setPassword("");]]></programlisting>
		</section>
		<section id="jdbc-SQLExceptionTranslator">
			<title><interfacename>SQLExceptionTranslator</interfacename></title>
			<para>
				<interfacename>SQLExceptionTranslator</interfacename> is an interface to be
				implemented by classes that can translate between <classname>SQLException</classname>s
				and Spring's own data-access-strategy-agnostic
				<classname>org.springframework.dao.DataAccessException</classname>.
			</para>
			<para>
				Implementations can be generic (for example, using SQLState codes
				for JDBC) or proprietary (for example, using Oracle error codes) for
				greater precision.
			</para>
			<para>
				<classname>SQLErrorCodeSQLExceptionTranslator</classname> is the
				implementation of SQLExceptionTranslator that is used by default. This
				implementation uses specific vendor codes. More precise than
				<literal>SQLState</literal> implementation, but vendor specific. The
				error code translations are based on codes held in a JavaBean type class
				named <classname>SQLErrorCodes</classname>. This class is created and
				populated by an <classname>SQLErrorCodesFactory</classname> which as the
				name suggests is a factory for creating <classname>SQLErrorCodes</classname>
				based on the contents of a configuration file named
				<literal>'sql-error-codes.xml'</literal>. This file is populated with vendor codes and
				based on the DatabaseProductName taken from the DatabaseMetaData, the
				codes for the current database are used.
			</para>
			<para>
				The <classname>SQLErrorCodeSQLExceptionTranslator</classname> applies
				the following matching rules:
				<itemizedlist spacing="compact">
					<listitem>
						<para>
							Try custom translation implemented by any subclass. Note
							that this class is concrete and is typically used itself, in which
							case this rule doesn't apply.
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							Apply error code matching. Error codes are obtained from the
							<classname>SQLErrorCodesFactory</classname> by default. This looks
							up error codes from	the classpath and keys into them from the
							database name from the database metadata.
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							Use the fallback translator. <classname>SQLStateSQLExceptionTranslator</classname>
							is the default fallback translator.
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
			</para>
			<para>
				<classname>SQLErrorCodeSQLExceptionTranslator</classname> can be extended the following way:
			</para>
			<programlisting><![CDATA[public class MySQLErrorCodesTranslator extends SQLErrorCodeSQLExceptionTranslator {
    protected DataAccessException customTranslate(String task, String sql, SQLException sqlex) {
        if (sqlex.getErrorCode() == -12345) {
            return new DeadlockLoserDataAccessException(task, sqlex);
        }
        return null;
    }
}]]></programlisting>
			<para>
				In this example the specific error code <literal>'-12345'</literal> is
				translated and any other errors are simply left to be translated by the
				default translator implementation. To use this custom translator, it is
				necessary to pass it to the <classname>JdbcTemplate</classname> using the
				method <literal>setExceptionTranslator</literal> and to use this
				<classname>JdbcTemplate</classname> for all of the data access processing
				where this translator is needed. Here is an example of how this custom
				translator can be used:
			</para>
            <programlisting><![CDATA[// create a JdbcTemplate and set data source 
JdbcTemplate jt = new JdbcTemplate(); 
jt.setDataSource(dataSource); 
// create a custom translator and set the DataSource for the default translation lookup 
MySQLErrorCodesTransalator tr = new MySQLErrorCodesTransalator(); 
tr.setDataSource(dataSource); 
jt.setExceptionTranslator(tr); 
// use the JdbcTemplate for this SqlUpdate 
SqlUpdate su = new SqlUpdate(); 
su.setJdbcTemplate(jt); 
su.setSql("update orders set shipping_charge = shipping_charge * 1.05"); 
su.compile(); 
su.update();]]></programlisting>
			<para>
				The custom translator is passed a data source because we still want
				the default translation to look up the error codes in
				<literal>sql-error-codes.xml</literal>.
			</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Executing statements</title>
			<para>
				To execute an SQL statement, there is very little code needed. All
				you need is a <interfacename>DataSource</interfacename> and a
				<classname>JdbcTemplate</classname>. Once you have that, you can use a
				number of convenience methods that are provided with the
				<classname>JdbcTemplate</classname>. Here is a short example showing what
				you need to include for a minimal but fully functional class that
				creates a new table.
			</para>
			<programlisting><![CDATA[import javax.sql.DataSource;
import org.springframework.jdbc.core.JdbcTemplate;

public class ExecuteAStatement {

    private JdbcTemplate jt;
    private DataSource dataSource;

    public void doExecute() {
        jt = new JdbcTemplate(dataSource);
        jt.execute("create table mytable (id integer, name varchar(100))"); 
    }

    public void setDataSource(DataSource dataSource) {
        this.dataSource = dataSource;
    }
}]]></programlisting>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Running Queries</title>
			<para>
				In addition to the execute methods, there is a large number of
				query methods. Some of these methods are intended to be used for queries
				that return a single value. Maybe you want to retrieve a count or a
				specific value from one row. If that is the case then you can use
				<literal>queryForInt(..)</literal>,<literal>queryForLong</literal> or
				<literal>queryForObject(..)</literal>. The latter will convert the returned
				JDBC Type to the Java class that is passed in as an argument. If the
				type conversion is invalid, then an
				<classname>InvalidDataAccessApiUsageException</classname> will be thrown.
				Here is an example that contains two query methods, one for an
				<literal>int</literal> and one that queries for a
				<classname>String</classname>.
			</para>
			<programlisting><![CDATA[import javax.sql.DataSource;
import org.springframework.jdbc.core.JdbcTemplate;

public class RunAQuery {

    private JdbcTemplate jt;
    private DataSource dataSource;
  
    public int getCount() {
        jt = new JdbcTemplate(dataSource);
        int count = jt.queryForInt("select count(*) from mytable");
        return count;
    }

    public String getName() {
        jt = new JdbcTemplate(dataSource);
        String name = (String) jt.queryForObject("select name from mytable", String.class);
        return name;
    }

    public void setDataSource(DataSource dataSource) {
        this.dataSource = dataSource;
    }
}]]></programlisting>
			<para>
				In addition to the single results query methods there are several
				methods that return a List with an entry for each row that the query
				returned. The most generic one is <literal>queryForList</literal> which
				returns a <interfacename>List</interfacename> where each entry is a
				<interfacename>Map</interfacename> with each entry in the map representing the
				column value for that row. If we add a method to the above example to
				retrieve a list of all the rows, it would look like this:
			</para>
			<programlisting><![CDATA[public List getList() {
    jt = new JdbcTemplate(dataSource);
    List rows = jt.queryForList("select * from mytable");
    return rows;
}]]></programlisting>
			<para>
				The list returned would look something like this:
			</para>
			<programlisting><![CDATA[[{name=Bob, id=1}, {name=Mary, id=2}]]]></programlisting>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Updating the database</title>
			<para>
				There are also a number of update methods that you can use. Find below
				an example where a column is updated for a certain primary key. In
				this example an SQL statement is used that has place holders for row
				parameters (most of the query and update methods have this
				functionality). Note that the parameter values are passed in as an array of
				objects (and this primitives have to be wrapped in the attendant wrapper
				reference classes).
			</para>
			<programlisting><![CDATA[import javax.sql.DataSource;

import org.springframework.jdbc.core.JdbcTemplate;

public class ExecuteAnUpdate {

    private JdbcTemplate jt;
    private DataSource dataSource;

    public void setName(int id, String name) {
        jt = new JdbcTemplate(dataSource);
        jt.update("update mytable set name = ? where id = ?", new Object[] {name, new Integer(id)});
    }

    public void setDataSource(DataSource dataSource) {
        this.dataSource = dataSource;
    }
}]]></programlisting>
		</section>
	</section>
	<section id="jdbc-datasource">
		<title>Controlling database connections</title>
		<section id="jdbc-DataSourceUtils">
			<title><classname>DataSourceUtils</classname></title>
			<para>
				The <classname>DataSourceUtils</classname> class is a convenient and
				powerful helper class that provides <literal>static</literal> methods to
				obtain connections from JNDI and close connections if necessary. It has
				support for thread-bound connections, e.g. for use with
				<classname>DataSourceTransactionManager</classname>.
			</para>
			<para>
				Note: the <literal>getDataSourceFromJndi(..)</literal> methods are
				targeted at applications that do not use a bean factory or application
				context. With the latter, it is preferable to preconfigure ones beans or
				even <classname>JdbcTemplate</classname> instances in the
				factory: <classname>JndiObjectFactoryBean</classname> can be used to fetch
				a <interfacename>DataSource</interfacename> from JNDI and give the
				<interfacename>DataSource</interfacename> bean reference to other
				beans. Switching to another <interfacename>DataSource</interfacename>
				is just a matter of configuration then: one can even replace the definition
				of the <interfacename>FactoryBean</interfacename> with a non-JNDI
				<interfacename>DataSource</interfacename>!
			</para>
		</section>
		<section id="jdbc-SmartDataSource">
			<title><interfacename>SmartDataSource</interfacename></title>
			<para>
				The <interfacename>SmartDataSource</interfacename> interface is to 
				be implemented by classes that can provide a connection to a relational
				database. Extends the <interfacename>DataSource</interfacename> interface to
				allow classes using it to query whether or not the connection should be
				closed after a given operation. This can sometimes be useful for efficiency,
				in the cases where one knows that one wants to reuse a connection.
			</para>
		</section>
		<section id="jdbc-AbstractDataSource">
			<title><classname>AbstractDataSource</classname></title>
			<para>
				This is an <literal>abstract</literal> base class for Spring's
				<interfacename>DataSource</interfacename> implementations, that takes
				care of the "uninteresting" glue. This is the class one would extend if
				one was writing one's own <interfacename>DataSource</interfacename>
				implementation.
			</para>
		</section>
		<section id="jdbc-SingleConnectionDataSource">
			<title><classname>SingleConnectionDataSource</classname></title>
			<para>
				The <classname>SingleConnectionDataSource</classname> class is an
				implementation of <literal>SmartDataSource</literal> that wraps a
				single connection which is not closed after use. Obviously, this is not
				multi-threading capable.
			</para>
			<para>
				If client code will call close in the assumption of a pooled
				connection, like when using persistence tools, set
				<literal>suppressClose</literal> to true. This will return a
				close-suppressing proxy instead of the physical connection. Be aware
				that you will not be able to cast this to a native Oracle Connection or
				the like anymore.
			</para>
			<para>
				This is primarily a test class. For example, it enables easy
				testing of code outside an application server, in conjunction with a
				simple JNDI environment. In contrast to
				<classname>DriverManagerDataSource</classname>, it reuses the same
				connection all the time, avoiding excessive creation of physical
				connections.
			</para>
		</section>
		<section id="jdbc-DriverManagerDataSource">
			<title><classname>DriverManagerDataSource</classname></title>
			<para>
				The <classname>DriverManagerDataSource</classname> class is an
				implementation of the <interfacename>SmartDataSource</interfacename>
				interface that  configures a plain old JDBC Driver via bean properties,
				and returns a new connection every time.
			</para>
			<para>
				This is potentially useful for test or standalone environments
				outside of a J2EE container, either as a <interfacename>DataSource</interfacename>
				bean in a respective ApplicationContext, or in conjunction with a simple
				JNDI environment. Pool-assuming <literal>Connection.close()</literal>
				calls will simply close the connection, so any <interfacename>DataSource</interfacename>-aware
				persistence code should work. However, using JavaBean style connection
				pools such as commons-dbcp is so easy, even in a test environment, that
				it is almost always preferable to use such a connection pool over
				<classname>DriverManagerDataSource</classname>.
			</para>
		</section>
		<section id="jdbc-TransactionAwareDataSourceProxy">
			<title><classname>TransactionAwareDataSourceProxy</classname></title>
			<para>
				<classname>TransactionAwareDataSourceProxy</classname> is a proxy for a target
				<interfacename>DataSource</interfacename>, which wraps that target
				<interfacename>DataSource</interfacename> to add awareness of
				Spring-managed transactions. In this respect it is similar to a
				transactional JNDI <interfacename>DataSource</interfacename> as provided by a J2EE
				server.
			</para>
			<note>
				<para>
				It should almost never be necessary or desireable to use this
				class, except when existing code exists which must be called and passed
				a standard JDBC <interfacename>DataSource</interfacename> interface implementation.
				In this case, it's possible to still have this code be usable, but
				participating in Spring managed transactions. It is generally preferable
				to write your own new code using the higher level abstractions for
				resource management, such as <classname>JdbcTemplate</classname> or
				<classname>DataSourceUtils</classname>.
				</para>
			</note>
			<para>
				<emphasis>(See the <classname>TransactionAwareDataSourceProxy</classname>
				Javadocs for more details.)</emphasis>
			</para>
		</section>
		<section id="jdbc-DataSourceTransactionManager">
			<title><classname>DataSourceTransactionManager</classname></title>
			<para>
				The <classname>DataSourceTransactionManager</classname> class is a
				<interfacename>PlatformTransactionManager</interfacename> implementation
				for single JDBC datasources. It binds a JDBC connection from the specified
				data source to the currently executing thread, potentially allowing for
				one thread connection per data source.
			</para>
			<para>
				Application code is required to retrieve the JDBC connection via
				<literal>DataSourceUtils.getConnection(DataSource)</literal> instead of
				J2EE's standard <literal>DataSource.getConnection</literal>. This is
				recommended anyway, as it throws unchecked
				<literal>org.springframework.dao</literal> exceptions instead of checked
				<classname>SQLException</classname>s. All framework classes like
				<classname>JdbcTemplate</classname> use this strategy implicitly. If not
				used with this transaction manager, the lookup strategy behaves exactly
				like the common one - it can thus be used in any case.
			</para>
			<para>
				The <classname>DataSourceTransactionManager</classname> class supports
				custom isolation levels, and timeouts that get applied as
				appropriate JDBC statement query timeouts. To support the latter,
				application code must either use <classname>JdbcTemplate</classname> or call
				<literal>DataSourceUtils.applyTransactionTimeout</literal> method for
				each created statement.
			</para>
			<para>
				This implementation can be used instead of
				<classname>JtaTransactionManager</classname> in the single resource case, as
				it does not require the container to support JTA. Switching between both
				is just a matter of configuration, if you stick to the required
				connection lookup pattern. Note that JTA does not support custom
				isolation levels!
			</para>
		</section>
	</section>
	<section id="jdbc-object">
		<title>Modeling JDBC operations as Java objects</title>
		<para>
			The <literal>org.springframework.jdbc.object</literal> package
			contains classes that allow one to access the database in a more
			object-oriented manner. By way of an example, one can execute queries
			and get the results back as a list containing business objects with
			the relational column data mapped to the properties of the business
			object. One can also execute stored procedures and run update, delete
			and insert statements.
		</para>
		<note>
			<para>
				There is a view (borne from experience acquired in the field)
				amongst some of the Spring developers that the various RDBMS
				operation classes described below (with the exception of the
				<link linkend="jdbc-StoredProcedure"><classname>StoredProcedure</classname></link>
				class) can often be replaced with straight <classname>JdbcTemplate</classname>
				calls... often it is just simpler to use (and plain easier to read) a DAO method
				that simply calls a method on a <classname>JdbcTemplate</classname> direct
				(as opposed to encapsulating a query as a full-blown class).
			</para>
			<para>
				It must be stressed however that this is just a <emphasis>view</emphasis>...
				if you feel that you are getting measurable value from using the RDBMS
				operation classes, feel free to continue using said classes.
			</para>
		</note>
		<section id="jdbc-SqlQuery">
			<title><classname>SqlQuery</classname></title>
			<para>
				<classname>SqlQuery</classname> is a reusable, threadsafe class that
				encapsulates an SQL query. Subclasses must implement the
				<literal>newResultReader()</literal> method to provide an object that
				can save the results while iterating over a supplied
				<interfacename>ResultSet</interfacename>. The
				<classname>SqlQuery</classname> class is rarely used directly since the
				<classname>MappingSqlQuery</classname> subclass provides a much more
				convenient implementation for mapping rows to Java classes. Other
				implementations that extend <classname>SqlQuery</classname> are
				<classname>MappingSqlQueryWithParameters</classname> and
				<classname>UpdatableSqlQuery</classname>.
			</para>
		</section>
		<section id="jdbc-MappingSqlQuery">
			<title><classname>MappingSqlQuery</classname></title>
			<para>
				<classname>MappingSqlQuery</classname> is a reusable query in which
				concrete subclasses must implement the abstract
      <literal>mapRow(ResultSet, int)</literal> method to convert each row of
      the supplied <interfacename>ResultSet</interfacename> into an object.</para>
			<para>
				Of all the various <interfacename>SqlQuery</interfacename> implementations,
				the <classname>MappingSqlQuery</classname> is
				the one used most often, and it is also the one that is the easiest to
				use.
			</para>
			<para>
				Find below a (brief) example of a custom query that maps the data from
				the customer table to an instance of the <classname>Customer</classname>
				class.
			</para>
			<programlisting><![CDATA[private class CustomerMappingQuery extends MappingSqlQuery {

    public CustomerMappingQuery(DataSource ds) {
        super(ds, "SELECT id, name FROM customer WHERE id = ?");
        super.declareParameter(new SqlParameter("id", Types.INTEGER));
        compile();
    }

    public Object mapRow(ResultSet rs, int rowNumber) throws SQLException {
        Customer cust = new Customer();
        cust.setId((Integer) rs.getObject("id"));
        cust.setName(rs.getString("name"));
        return cust;
    } 
}]]></programlisting>
			<para>
				We provide a constructor for this customer query that takes the
				<interfacename>DataSource</interfacename> as the only parameter. In this constructor
				we call the constructor on the superclass with the
				<interfacename>DataSource</interfacename> and the SQL that should be executed to
				retrieve the rows for this query. This SQL will be used to create a
				<interfacename>PreparedStatement</interfacename> so it may contain place holders for
				any parameters to be passed in during execution. Each parameter must be
				declared using the <literal>declareParameter</literal> method passing in
				an <classname>SqlParameter</classname>. The <classname>SqlParameter</classname>
				takes a name and the JDBC type as defined in
				<classname>java.sql.Types</classname>. After all parameters have been
				defined we call the <literal>compile()</literal> method so the statement
				can be prepared and later be executed.
			</para>
			<para>
				Let's take a look at the code where this custom query is
				instantiated and executed:
			</para>
			<programlisting><![CDATA[public Customer getCustomer(Integer id) {
    CustomerMappingQuery custQry = new CustomerMappingQuery(dataSource); 
    Object[] parms = new Object[1];
    parms[0] = id;
    List customers = custQry.execute(parms);
    if (customers.size() > 0) {
        return (Customer) customers.get(0);
    }
    else {
        return null;
    }
}]]></programlisting>
			<para>
				The method in this example retrieves the customer with the id that
				is passed in as the only parameter. After creating an instance of the
				<classname>CustomerMappingQuery</classname> class we create an array of
				objects that will contain all parameters that are passed in. In this
				case there is only one parameter and it is passed in as an
				<classname>Integer</classname>. Now we are ready to execute the query using
				this array of parameters and we get a <literal>List</literal> that
				contains a <classname>Customer</classname> object for each row that was
				returned for our query. In this case it will only be one entry if there
				was a match.
			</para>
		</section>
		<section id="jdbc-SqlUpdate">
			<title><classname>SqlUpdate</classname></title>
			<para>
				The <classname>SqlUpdate</classname> class encapsulates an SQL update.
				Like a query, an update object is reusable. Like all
				<classname>RdbmsOperation</classname> classes, an update
				can have parameters and is defined in SQL.
			</para>
			<para>
				This class provides a number of <literal>update()</literal> methods
				analogous to the <literal>execute()</literal> methods of query objects.
			</para>
			<para>
				This class is concrete. Although it can be subclassed (for example
				to add a custom update method) it can easily be parameterized by setting
				SQL and declaring parameters.
			</para>
			<programlisting><![CDATA[import java.sql.Types;

import javax.sql.DataSource;

import org.springframework.jdbc.core.SqlParameter;
import org.springframework.jdbc.object.SqlUpdate;

public class UpdateCreditRating extends SqlUpdate {

    public UpdateCreditRating(DataSource ds) {
        setDataSource(ds);
        setSql("update customer set credit_rating = ? where id = ?");
        declareParameter(new SqlParameter(Types.NUMERIC));
        declareParameter(new SqlParameter(Types.NUMERIC));
        compile();
    }

    /**
     * @param id for the Customer to be updated
     * @param rating the new value for credit rating
     * @return number of rows updated
     */
    public int run(int id, int rating) {
        Object[] params =
            new Object[] {
                new Integer(rating),
                new Integer(id)};
        return update(params);
    }
}]]></programlisting>
		</section>
		<section id="jdbc-StoredProcedure">
			<title><classname>StoredProcedure</classname></title>
			<para>
				The <classname>StoredProcedure</classname> class is a superclass for object
				abstractions of RDBMS stored procedures. This class is <literal>abstract</literal>,
				and its various <literal>execute(..)</literal> methods have
				<literal>protected</literal> access, preventing use other than through a
				subclass that offers tighter typing.
			</para>
			<para>
				The inherited <literal>sql</literal> property will be the name of the
				stored procedure in the RDBMS. Note that JDBC 3.0 introduces named
				parameters, although the other features provided by this class are
				still necessary in JDBC 3.0.
			</para>
			<para>
				Here is an example of a program that calls a function, <literal>sysdate()</literal>,
				that comes with any Oracle database. To use the stored procedure
				functionality one has to create a class that extends
				<classname>StoredProcedure</classname>. There are no input parameters, but
				there is an output parameter that is declared as a date type using the class
				<classname>SqlOutParameter</classname>. The <literal>execute()</literal>
				method returns a map with an entry for each declared output parameter
				using the parameter name as the key.
			</para>
			<programlisting><![CDATA[import java.sql.Types;
import java.util.HashMap;
import java.util.Iterator;
import java.util.Map;

import javax.sql.DataSource;

import org.springframework.jdbc.core.SqlOutParameter;
import org.springframework.jdbc.datasource.*;
import org.springframework.jdbc.object.StoredProcedure;

public class TestStoredProcedure {

    public static void main(String[] args)  {
        TestStoredProcedure t = new TestStoredProcedure();
        t.test();
        System.out.println("Done!");
    }
    
    void test() {
        DriverManagerDataSource ds = new DriverManagerDataSource();
        ds.setDriverClassName("oracle.jdbc.OracleDriver");
        ds.setUrl("jdbc:oracle:thin:@localhost:1521:mydb");
        ds.setUsername("scott");
        ds.setPassword("tiger");

        MyStoredProcedure sproc = new MyStoredProcedure(ds);
        Map results = sproc.execute();
        printMap(results);
    }

    private class MyStoredProcedure extends StoredProcedure {
        
        private static final String SQL = "sysdate";

        public MyStoredProcedure(DataSource ds) {
            setDataSource(ds);
            setFunction(true);
            setSql(SQL);
            declareParameter(new SqlOutParameter("date", Types.DATE));
            compile();
        }

        public Map execute() {
            ]]><lineannotation>// the 'sysdate' sproc has no input parameters, so an empty Map is supplied...</lineannotation><![CDATA[
            return execute(new HashMap());
        }
    }

    private static void printMap(Map results) {
        for (Iterator it = results.entrySet().iterator(); it.hasNext(); ) {
            System.out.println(it.next());  
        }
    }
}]]></programlisting>
		<para>
	        Find below an example of a <classname>StoredProcedure</classname> that
	        has two output parameters (in this case Oracle cursors).
		</para>
		<programlisting><![CDATA[import oracle.jdbc.driver.OracleTypes;
import org.springframework.jdbc.core.SqlOutParameter;
import org.springframework.jdbc.object.StoredProcedure;

import javax.sql.DataSource;
import java.util.HashMap;
import java.util.Map;

public class TitlesAndGenresStoredProcedure extends StoredProcedure {

    private static final String SPROC_NAME = "AllTitlesAndGenres";

    public TitlesAndGenresStoredProcedure(DataSource dataSource) {
        super(dataSource, SPROC_NAME);
        declareParameter(new SqlOutParameter("titles", OracleTypes.CURSOR, new TitleMapper()));
        declareParameter(new SqlOutParameter("genres", OracleTypes.CURSOR, new GenreMapper()));
        compile();
    }

    public Map execute() {
        ]]><lineannotation>// again, this sproc has no input parameters, so an empty Map is supplied...</lineannotation><![CDATA[
        return super.execute(new HashMap());
    }
}]]></programlisting>
			<para>
				Notice how the overloaded variants of the <literal>declareParameter(..)</literal>
				method that have been used in the <classname>TitlesAndGenresStoredProcedure</classname>
				constructor are passed <interfacename>RowMapper</interfacename> implementation
				instances; this is a very convenient and powerful way to reuse existing
				functionality. (The code for the two <interfacename>RowMapper</interfacename>
				implementations is provided below in the interest of completeness.)
			</para>
			<para>
				Firstly the <classname>TitleMapper</classname> class, which simply
				maps a <interfacename>ResultSet</interfacename> to a <classname>Title</classname>
				domain object for each row in the supplied <interfacename>ResultSet</interfacename>.
			</para>
			<programlisting><![CDATA[import com.foo.sprocs.domain.Title;
import org.springframework.jdbc.core.RowMapper;

import java.sql.ResultSet;
import java.sql.SQLException;

public final class TitleMapper implements RowMapper {
    
    public Object mapRow(ResultSet rs, int rowNum) throws SQLException {
        Title title = new Title();
        title.setId(rs.getLong("id"));
        title.setName(rs.getString("name"));
        return title;
    }
}]]></programlisting>
			<para>
				Secondly, the <classname>GenreMapper</classname> class, which again simply
				maps a <interfacename>ResultSet</interfacename> to a <classname>Genre</classname>
				domain object for each row in the supplied <interfacename>ResultSet</interfacename>.
			</para>
			<programlisting><![CDATA[import org.springframework.jdbc.core.RowMapper;

import java.sql.ResultSet;
import java.sql.SQLException;

import com.foo.domain.Genre;

public final class GenreMapper implements RowMapper {
    
    public Object mapRow(ResultSet rs, int rowNum) throws SQLException {
        return new Genre(rs.getString("name"));
    }
}]]></programlisting>
			<para>
				If one needs to pass parameters to a stored procedure (i.e. the
				stored procedure has been declared as having one or more input
				parameters in its definition in the RDBMS), one would code a
				strongly typed <literal>execute(..)</literal> method which would delegate
				to the superclass' (untyped) <literal>execute(Map parameters)</literal>
				(which has <literal>protected</literal> access); to wit...
			</para>
		<programlisting><![CDATA[import oracle.jdbc.driver.OracleTypes;
import org.springframework.jdbc.core.SqlOutParameter;
import org.springframework.jdbc.object.StoredProcedure;

import javax.sql.DataSource;
import java.util.HashMap;
import java.util.Map;

public class TitlesAfterDateStoredProcedure extends StoredProcedure {

    private static final String SPROC_NAME = "TitlesAfterDate";
    private static final String CUTOFF_DATE_PARAM = "cutoffDate";

    public TitlesAfterDateStoredProcedure(DataSource dataSource) {
        super(dataSource, SPROC_NAME);
        declaraParameter(new SqlParameter(CUTOFF_DATE_PARAM, Types.DATE);
        declareParameter(new SqlOutParameter("titles", OracleTypes.CURSOR, new TitleMapper()));
        compile();
    }

    public Map execute(Date cutoffDate) {
        Map inputs = new HashMap();
        inputs.put(CUTOFF_DATE_PARAM, cutoffDate);
        return super.execute(inputs);
    }
}]]></programlisting>
		</section>
		<section id="jdbc-SqlFunction">
			<title><classname>SqlFunction</classname></title>
			<para>
				The <classname>SqlFunction</classname> RDBMS operation class encapsulates an
				SQL "function" wrapper for a query that returns a single row of
				results. The default behavior is to return an <literal>int</literal>, but that
				can be overridden by using the methods with an extra return type parameter.
				This is similar to using the <literal>queryForXxx</literal> methods of
				the <classname>JdbcTemplate</classname>. The advantage with
				<classname>SqlFunction</classname> is that you don't have to create the
				<classname>JdbcTemplate</classname>, it is done behind the scenes.
			</para>
			<para>
				This class is intended to use to call SQL functions that return a
				single result using a query like "select user()" or "select sysdate from
				dual". It is not intended for calling more complex stored functions or
				for using a <classname>CallableStatement</classname> to invoke a stored
				procedure or stored function. (Use the <classname>StoredProcedure</classname> or
				<classname>SqlCall</classname> classes for this type of processing).
			</para>
			<para>
				<classname>SqlFunction</classname> is a concrete class, and there is typically
				no need to subclass it. Code using this package can create an object of this type,
				declaring SQL and parameters, and then invoke the appropriate run method
				repeatedly to execute the function. Here is an example of retrieving the
				count of rows from a table:
			</para>
			<programlisting><![CDATA[public int countRows() {
    SqlFunction sf = new SqlFunction(dataSource, "select count(*) from mytable");
    sf.compile();
    return sf.run();
}]]></programlisting>
		</section>
	</section>
</chapter>