<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="mvc">
  <title>Web MVC framework</title>

  <sect1 id="mvc-introduction">
    <title>Introduction to the web MVC framework</title>

    <para>Spring's web MVC framework is designed around a DispatcherServlet
    that dispatches requests to handlers, with configurable handler mappings,
    view resolution, locale and theme resolution as well as support for upload
    files. The default handler is a very simple Controller interface, just
    offering a <literal>ModelAndView handleRequest(request,response)</literal>
    method. This can already be used for application controllers, but you will
    prefer the included implementation hierarchy, consisting of, for example
    <literal>AbstractController</literal>,
    <literal>AbstractCommandController</literal> and
    <literal>SimpleFormController</literal>. Application controllers will
    typically be subclasses of those. Note that you can choose an appropriate
    base class: If you don't have a form, you don't need a FormController.
    This is a major difference to Struts.</para>

    <para>You can use any object as a command or form object - there's no need
    to implement an interface or derive from a base class. Spring's data
    binding is highly flexible, for example, it treats type mismatches as
    validation errors that can be evaluated by the application, not as system
    errors. So you don't need to duplicate your business objects' properties
    as Strings in your form objects, just to be able to handle invalid
    submissions, or to convert the Strings properly. Instead, it is often
    preferable to bind directly to your business objects. This is another
    major difference to Struts which is built around required base classes
    like <literal>Action</literal> and <literal>ActionForm</literal> - for
    every type of action.</para>

    <para>Compared to WebWork, Spring has more differentiated object roles. It
    supports the notion of a Controller, an optional command or form object,
    and a model that gets passed to the view. The model will normally include
    the command or form object but also arbitrary reference data. Instead, a
    WebWork Action combines all those roles into one single object. WebWork
    does allow you to use existing business objects as part of your form, but
    only by making them bean properties of the respective Action class.
    Finally, the same Action instance that handles the request is used for
    evaluation and form population in the view. Thus, reference data needs to
    be modeled as bean properties of the Action too. These are arguably too
    many roles for one object.</para>

    <para>Spring's view resolution is extremely flexible. A Controller
    implementation can even write a view directly to the response, returning
    null as ModelAndView. In the normal case, a ModelAndView instance consists
    of a view name and a model Map, containing bean names and corresponding
    objects (like a command or form, containing reference data). View name
    resolution is highly configurable, either via bean names, via a properties
    file, or via your own ViewResolver implementation. The abstract model Map
    allows for complete abstraction of the view technology, without any
    hassle. Any renderer can be integrated directly, whether JSP, Velocity, or
    any other rendering technology. The model Map is simply transformed into
    an appropriate format, such as JSP request attributes or a Velocity
    template model.</para>

    <sect2 id="mvc-introduction-pluggability">
      <title>Pluggability of other MVC implementations</title>

      <para>There are several reasons why some projects will prefer to use
      other MVC implementations. Many teams expect to leverage their existing
      investment in skills and tools. In addition, there is a large body of
      knowledge and experience avalailable for the Struts framework. Thus, if
      you can live with Struts' architectural flaws, it can still be a viable
      choice for the web layer. The same applies to WebWork and other web MVC
      frameworks.</para>

      <para>If you don't want to use Spring's web MVC, but intend to leverage
      other solutions that Spring offers, you can integrate the web MVC
      framework of your choice with Spring easily. Simply start up a Spring
      root application context via its ContextLoaderListener, and access it
      via its ServletContext attribute (or Spring's respective helper method)
      from within a Struts or WebWork action. Note that there aren't any
      "plugins" involved, so no dedicated integration is necessary. From the
      web layer's point of view, you'll simply use Spring as a library, with
      the root application context instance as the entry point.</para>

      <para>All your registered beans and all of Spring's services can be at
      your fingertips even without Spring's web MVC. Spring doesn't compete
      with Struts or WebWork in this scenario, it just addresses the many
      areas that the pure web MVC frameworks don't, from bean configuration to
      data access and transaction handling. So you are able to enrich your
      application with a Spring middle tier and/or data access tier, even if
      you just want to use, for example, the transaction abstraction with JDBC
      or Hibernate.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="mvc-features">
      <title>Features of Spring MVC</title>

      <para>Spring's web module provides a wealth of unique web support
      features, including:</para>

      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>Clear separation of roles - controller, validator, command
          object, form object, model object, DispatcherServlet, handler
          mapping, view resolver, etc. Each role can be fulfilled by a
          specialized object.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Powerful and straightforward configuration of both framework
          and application classes as JavaBeans, including easy referencing
          across contexts, such as from web controllers to business objects
          and validators.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Adaptability, non-intrusiveness. Use whatever controller
          subclass you need (plain, command, form, wizard, multi-action, or a
          custom one) for a given scenario instead of deriving from a single
          controller for everything.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Reusable business code - no need for duplication. You can use
          existing business objects as command or form objects instead of
          mirroring them in order to extend a particular framework base
          class.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Customizable binding and validation - type mismatches as
          application-level validation errors that keep the offending value,
          localized date and number binding, etc instead of String-only form
          objects with manual parsing and conversion to business
          objects.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Customizable handler mapping and view resolution - handler
          mapping and view resolution strategies range from simple URL-based
          configuration, to sophisticated, purpose-built resolution
          strategies. This is more flexible than some web MVC frameworks which
          mandate a particular technique.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Flexible model transfer - model transfer via a name/value Map
          supports easy integration with any view technology.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Customizable locale and theme resolution, support for JSPs
          with or without Spring tag library, support for JSTL, support for
          Velocity without the need for extra bridges, etc.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>A simple yet powerful tag library known as the Spring tag library
          that provides support for features such as data binding and themes. The custom tags
          allow for maximum flexibility in terms of markup code.
          For information on the tag library descriptor, see <xref linkend="spring.tld" /></para>
        </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>A convenience form tag library, introduced in Spring 2.0, that makes writing JSP pages much easier.
            For information on the tag library descriptor, see <xref linkend="spring-form.tld" /></para>
          </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="mvc-servlet">
    <title>The <literal>DispatcherServlet</literal></title>

    <para>Spring's web MVC framework is, like many other web MVC frameworks, a
    request-driven web MVC framework, designed around a servlet that
    dispatches requests to controllers and offers other functionality
    facilitating the development of web applications. Spring's
    <literal>DispatcherServlet</literal> however, does more than just that. It
    is completely integrated with the Spring ApplicationContext and allows you
    to use every other feature Spring has.</para>

    <para>Like ordinary servlets, the DispatcherServlet is declared in the
    <literal>web.xml</literal> of your web application. Requests that you want
    the DispatcherServlet to handle, will have to be mapped, using a URL
    mapping in the same <literal>web.xml</literal> file.</para>

    <programlisting>&lt;web-app&gt;
    ...
    &lt;servlet&gt;
        &lt;servlet-name&gt;example&lt;/servlet-name&gt;
        &lt;servlet-class&gt;org.springframework.web.servlet.DispatcherServlet&lt;/servlet-class&gt;
        &lt;load-on-startup&gt;1&lt;/load-on-startup&gt;
    &lt;/servlet&gt;
    &lt;servlet-mapping&gt;
        &lt;servlet-name&gt;example&lt;/servlet-name&gt;
        &lt;url-pattern&gt;*.form&lt;/url-pattern&gt;
    &lt;/servlet-mapping&gt;
&lt;/web-app&gt;</programlisting>

    <para>In the example above, all requests ending with
    <literal>.form</literal> will be handled by the DispatcherServlet. The
    DispatcherServlet now needs to be configured.</para>

    <para>As illustrated in <xref linkend="context-introduction" />,
    ApplicationContexts in Spring can be scoped. In the web MVC framework,
		each DispatcherServlet has its own <literal>WebApplicationContext</literal>,
    which inherits all the beans already defined in in the Root WebApplicationContext.
		These inherited beans defined can be overridden in the servlet-specific scope,
    and new scope-specific beans can be defined local to a given servlet instance.</para>
		<para>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject role="fo">
					<!-- TODO: replace with SVG version -->
					<imagedata fileref="images/mvc-contexts.gif" format="GIF" align="center" />
				</imageobject>
				<imageobject role="html">
					<imagedata fileref="images/mvc-contexts.gif" format="GIF" align="center" />
				</imageobject>
				<caption>
					<para>Context hierarchy in Spring MVC</para>
				</caption>
			</mediaobject>
		</para>

    <para>The framework will, on initialization of a DispatcherServlet,
    <emphasis>look for a file named <literal>[servlet-name]-servlet.xml</literal></emphasis>
    in the <literal>WEB-INF</literal> directory of your web application and
    create the beans defined there (overriding the definitions of any beans
    defined with the same name in the global scope).</para>

    <para>The config location used by the DispatcherServlet can be modified
    through a servlet initialization parameter (see below for details).</para>

    <para>The <literal>WebApplicationContext</literal> is just an ordinary
    ApplicationContext that has some extra features necessary for web
    applications. It differs from a normal ApplicationContext in that it is
    capable of resolving themes (see <xref linkend="mvc-themeresolver" />),
    and that is knows which servlet it is associated with (by having a link to
    the <literal>ServletContext</literal>). The WebApplicationContext is bound
    in the ServletContext, and using <literal>RequestContextUtils</literal>
    you can always lookup the WebApplicationContext in case you need
    it.</para>

    <para>The Spring DispatcherServlet has a couple of special beans it uses,
    in order to be able to process requests and render the appropriate views.
    These beans are included in the Spring framework and can be configured in
    the WebApplicationContext, just as any other bean would be configured.
    Each of those beans, is described in more detail below. Right now, we'll
    just mention them, just to let you know they exist and to enable us to go
    on talking about the DispatcherServlet. For most of the beans, defaults
    are provided so you don't have to worry about configuring them.</para>

    <table frame="all">
      <title>Special beans in the WebApplicationContext</title>

      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="c1" colwidth="1*" />

        <colspec colname="c2" colwidth="4*" />

        <thead>
          <row>
            <entry>Expression</entry>

            <entry>Explanation</entry>
          </row>
        </thead>

        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>handler mapping(s)</entry>

            <entry>(<xref linkend="mvc-handlermapping" />) a list of pre- and
            postprocessors and controllers that will be executed if they match
            certain criteria (for instance a matching URL specified with the
            controller)</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>controller(s)</entry>

            <entry>(<xref linkend="mvc-controller" />) the beans providing the
            actual functionality (or at least, access to the functionality) as
            part of the MVC triad</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>view resolver</entry>

            <entry>(<xref linkend="mvc-viewresolver" />) capable of resolving
            view names to views, used by the DispatcherServlet</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>locale resolver</entry>

            <entry>(<xref linkend="mvc-localeresolver" />) capable of
            resolving the locale a client is using, in order to be able to
            offer internationalized views</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>theme resolver</entry>

            <entry>(<xref linkend="mvc-themeresolver" />) capable of resolving
            themes your web application can use, for example, to offer
            personalized layouts</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>multipart resolver</entry>

            <entry>(<xref linkend="mvc-multipart" />) offers functionality to
            process file uploads from HTML forms</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>handlerexception resolver</entry>

            <entry>(<xref linkend="mvc-exceptionhandlers" />) offers
            functionality to map exceptions to views or implement other more
            complex exception handling code</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>

    <para>When a DispatcherServlet is setup for use and a request comes in for
    that specific DispatcherServlet it starts processing it. The list below
    describes the complete process a request goes through if handled by a
    DispatcherServlet: <orderedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>The WebApplicationContext is searched for and bound in the
          request as an attribute in order for the controller and other
          elements in the process to use. It is bound by default under the key
          <literal>DispatcherServlet.WEB_APPLICATION_CONTEXT_ATTRIBUTE</literal>.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The locale resolver is bound to the request to let elements in
          the process resolve the locale to use when processing the request
          (rendering the view, preparing data, etc.) If you don't use the
          resolver, it won't affect anything, so if you don't need locale
          resolving, you don't have to use it.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The theme resolver is bound to the request to let elements
          such as views determine which theme to use. The theme resolver does
          not affect anything if you don't use it, so if you don't need themes
          you can just ignore it.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>If a multipart resolver is specified, the request is inspected
          for multiparts and if they are found, it is wrapped in a
          <literal>MultipartHttpServletRequest</literal> for further
          processing by other elements in the process. (See <xref
          linkend="mvc-multipart-resolver" /> for further information about
          multipart handling).</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>An appropriate handler is searched for. If a handler is found,
          the execution chain associated with the handler (preprocessors,
          postprocessors, controllers) will be executed in order to prepare a
          model.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>If a model is returned, the view is rendered, using the view
          resolver that has been configured with the WebApplicationContext. If
          no model is returned (which could be due to a pre- or postprocessor
          intercepting the request, for example, for security reasons), no
          view is rendered, since the request could already have been
          fulfilled.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist></para>

    <para>Exceptions that might be thrown during processing of the request get
    picked up by any of the handlerexception resolvers that are declared in
    the WebApplicationContext. Using these exception resolvers you can define
    custom behavior in case such exceptions get thrown.</para>

    <para>The Spring DispatcherServlet also has support for returning the
    <emphasis>last-modification-date</emphasis>, as specified by the Servlet
    API. The process of determining the last modification date for a specific
    request, is simple. The DispatcherServlet will first lookup an appropriate
    handler mapping and test if the handler that is found <emphasis>implements
    the interface <literal>LastModified</literal></emphasis> and if so, the
    value of <literal>long getLastModified(request)</literal> is returned to
    the client.</para>

    <para>You can customize Spring's DispatcherServlet by adding context
    parameters in the <literal>web.xml</literal> file or servlet init
    parameters. The possibilities are listed below.</para>

    <table frame="all">
      <title>DispatcherServlet initialization parameters</title>

      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="c1" colwidth="1*" />

        <colspec colname="c2" colwidth="4*" />

        <thead>
          <row>
            <entry>Parameter</entry>

            <entry>Explanation</entry>
          </row>
        </thead>

        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry><literal>contextClass</literal></entry>

            <entry>Class that implements
            <literal>WebApplicationContext</literal>, which will be used to
            instantiate the context used by this servlet. If this parameter
            isn't specified, the <literal>XmlWebApplicationContext</literal>
            will be used.</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><literal>contextConfigLocation</literal></entry>

            <entry>String which is passed to the context instance (specified
            by <literal>contextClass</literal>) to indicate where context(s)
            can be found. The String is potentially split up into multiple
            strings (using a comma as a delimiter) to support multiple
            contexts (in case of multiple context locations, of beans that are
            defined twice, the latest takes precedence).</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>namespace</entry>

            <entry>the namespace of the
            <literal>WebApplicationContext</literal>. Defaults to
            <literal>[server-name]-servlet</literal>.</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="mvc-controller">
    <title>Controllers</title>

    <para>The notion of a controller is part of the MVC design pattern.
    Controllers define application behavior, or at least provide access to the
    application behavior. Controllers interpret user input and transform the
    user input into a sensible model which will be represented to the user by
    the view. Spring has implemented the notion of a controller in a very
    abstract way enabling a wide variety of different kinds of controllers to
    be created. Spring contains formcontroller, commandcontroller, controllers
    that execute wizard-style logic, and more.</para>

    <para>Spring's basis for the controller architecture is the
    <literal>org.springframework.web.servlet.mvc.Controller</literal>
    interface, which is listed below. <programlisting>public interface Controller {

    /**
     * Process the request and return a ModelAndView object which the DispatcherServlet
     * will render.
     */
    ModelAndView handleRequest(
        HttpServletRequest request,
        HttpServletResponse response)
    throws Exception;
}</programlisting> As you can see, the <literal>Controller</literal> interface
    requires a single method that should be capable of handling a request and
    returning an appropriate model and view. These three concepts are the
    basis for the Spring MVC implementation -
    <emphasis>ModelAndView</emphasis> and <emphasis>Controller</emphasis>.
    While the <literal>Controller</literal> interface is quite abstract,
    Spring offers a lot of controllers that already contain a lot of the
    functionality you might need. The <literal>Controller</literal> interface
    just defines the most common functionality required of every controller -
    handling a request and returning a model and a view.</para>

    <sect2 id="mvc-controller-abstractcontroller">
      <title>AbstractController and WebContentGenerator</title>

      <para>Of course, just a controller interface isn't enough. To provide a
      basic infrastructure, all of Spring's Controllers inherit from
      AbstractController, a class offering caching support and, for example,
      the setting of the mimetype.</para>

      <table frame="all" id="mvc-controller-abstract-features">
        <title>Features offered by the
        <literal>AbstractController</literal></title>

        <tgroup cols="2">
          <colspec colname="c1" colwidth="1*" />

          <colspec colname="c2" colwidth="3*" />

          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>Feature</entry>

              <entry>Explanation</entry>
            </row>
          </thead>

          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry><literal>supportedMethods</literal></entry>

              <entry>indicates what methods this controller should accept.
              Usually this is set to both <literal>GET</literal> and
              <literal>POST</literal>, but you can modify this to reflect the
              method you want to support. If a request is received with a
              method that is not supported by the controller, the client will
              be informed of this (using a
              <literal>ServletException)</literal>).</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><literal>requiresSession</literal></entry>

              <entry>indicates whether or not this controller requires a
              session to do its work. This feature is offered to all
              controllers. If a session is not present when such a controller
              receives a request, the user is informed using a
              <literal>ServletException</literal>.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><literal>synchronizeSession</literal></entry>

              <entry>use this if you want handling by this controller to be
              synchronized on the user's session. To be more specific,
              extending controller will override the
              <literal>handleRequestInternal</literal> method, which will be
              synchronized if you specify this variable.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><literal>cacheSeconds</literal></entry>

              <entry>when you want a controller to generate a caching
              directive in the HTTP response, specify a positive integer here.
              By default it is set to <emphasis>-1</emphasis> so no caching
              directives will be included.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><literal>useExpiresHeader</literal></entry>

              <entry>tweaks your controllers to specify the HTTP 1.0
              compatible <emphasis>"Expires"</emphasis> header. By default
              it's set to true, so you won't have to change it.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><literal>useCacheHeader</literal></entry>

              <entry>tweaks your controllers to specify the HTTP 1.1
              compatible <emphasis>"Cache-Control"</emphasis> header. By
              default this is set to true so you won't have to change
              it.</entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>

      <para><emphasis>The last two properties are actually part of the
      <literal>WebContentGenerator</literal> which is the superclass of
      <literal>AbstractController</literal> but are included here for
      completeness.</emphasis></para>

      <para>When using the AbstractController as a baseclass for your
      controllers (which is <emphasis>not</emphasis> recommended since there
      are a lot of other controllers that might already do the job for you)
      you only have to override the
      <literal>handleRequestInternal(HttpServletRequest,
      HttpServletResponse)</literal> method, implement your logic, and return
      a <literal>ModelAndView</literal> object. Here is short example
      consisting of a class and a declaration in the web application context.
      <programlisting>package samples;

public class SampleController extends AbstractController {

    public ModelAndView handleRequestInternal(
        HttpServletRequest request,
        HttpServletResponse response)
    throws Exception {
        ModelAndView mav = new ModelAndView("foo");
        mav.addObject("message", "Hello World!");
        return mav;        
    }
}</programlisting> <programlisting>&lt;bean id="sampleController" class="samples.SampleController"&gt;
    &lt;property name="cacheSeconds" value="120"/&gt;
&lt;/bean&gt;</programlisting> The class above and the declaration in the web
      application context is all you need besides setting up a handler mapping
      (see <xref linkend="mvc-handlermapping" />) to get this very simple
      controller working. This controller will generate caching directives
      telling the client to cache things for 2 minutes before rechecking. This
      controller returns an hard-coded view (hmm, not so nice), named index
      (see <xref linkend="mvc-viewresolver" /> for more information about
      views).</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="mvc-controller-othersimplecontrollers">
      <title>Other simple controllers</title>

      <para>Although you can extend AbstractController, Spring provides a
      number of concrete implementations which offer functionality that is
      commonly used in simple MVC applications. The
      <literal>ParameterizableViewController</literal> is basically the same
      as the example above, except for the fact that you can specify the view
      name that it will return in the web application context (ahhh, no need
      to hard-code the viewname).</para>

      <para>The <literal>UrlFilenameViewController</literal> inspects the URL
      and retrieves the filename of the file request (the filename of
      <literal>http://www.springframework.org/index.html</literal> is
      <literal>index</literal>) and uses that as a viewname. Nothing more to
      it.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="mvc-controller-multiaction">
      <title>The <literal>MultiActionController</literal></title>

      <para>Spring offers a multi-action controller with which you aggregate
      multiple actions into one controller, grouping functionality together.
      The multi-action controller lives in a separate package -
      <literal>org.springframework.web.servlet.mvc.multiaction</literal> - and
      is capable of mapping requests to method names and then invoking the
      right method name. Using the multi-action controller is especially handy
      when you have a lot of common functionality in one controller, but want
      to have multiple entry points to the controller, for example, to tweak
      behavior.</para>

      <table frame="all" id="mvc-controller-multiaction-features">
        <title>Features offered by the
        <literal>MultiActionController</literal></title>

        <tgroup cols="2">
          <colspec colname="c1" colwidth="1*" />

          <colspec colname="c2" colwidth="3*" />

          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>Feature</entry>

              <entry>Explanation</entry>
            </row>
          </thead>

          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry><literal>delegate</literal></entry>

              <entry>there are two usage-scenarios for the
              MultiActionController. Either you subclass the
              MultiActionController and specify the methods that will be
              resolved by the MethodNameResolver on the subclass (in which
              case you don't need to set the delegate), or you define a
              delegate object, on which methods resolved by the Resolver will
              be invoked. If you choose this scenario, you will have to define
              the delegate using this configuration parameter as a
              collaborator.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><literal>methodNameResolver</literal></entry>

              <entry>somehow the MultiActionController will need to resolve
              the method it has to invoke, based on the request that came in.
              You can define a resolver that is capable of doing that using
              this configuration parameter.</entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>

      <para>Methods defined for a multi-action controller need to conform to
      the following signature: <programlisting>// actionName can be replaced by any methodname
ModelAndView actionName(HttpServletRequest, HttpServletResponse);</programlisting>
      Method overloading is not allowed since it would confuse the
      MultiActionController. Furthermore, you can define <emphasis>exception
      handlers</emphasis> capable of handling exceptions that are thrown by
      the methods you specify. Exception handler methods need to return a
      ModelAndView object, just as any other action method and need to conform
      to the following signature: <programlisting>// anyMeaningfulName can be replaced by any methodname
ModelAndView anyMeaningfulName(HttpServletRequest, HttpServletResponse, ExceptionClass);</programlisting>
      The <literal>ExceptionClass</literal> can be <emphasis>any</emphasis>
      exception, as long as it's a subclass of
      <literal>java.lang.Exception</literal> or
      <literal>java.lang.RuntimeException</literal>.</para>

      <para>The <literal>MethodNameResolver</literal> is supposed to resolve
      method names based on the request coming in. There are three resolvers
      at your disposal, but of course you can implement more of them yourself
      if you want to. <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
          <listitem>
            <para><literal>ParameterMethodNameResolver</literal> - capable of
            resolving a request parameter and using that as the method name
            (<literal>http://www.sf.net/index.view?testParam=testIt</literal>
            will result in a method <literal>testIt(HttpServletRequest,
            HttpServletResponse)</literal> being called). The
            <literal>paramName</literal> configuration parameter specifies the
            parameter that is inspected).</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><literal>InternalPathMethodNameResolver</literal> -
            retrieves the filename from the path and uses that as the method
            name (<literal>http://www.sf.net/testing.view</literal> will
            result in a method <literal>testing(HttpServletRequest,
            HttpServletResponse)</literal> being called).</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><literal>PropertiesMethodNameResolver</literal> - uses a
            user-defined properties object with request URLs mapped to
            methodnames. When the properties contain
            <literal>/index/welcome.html=doIt</literal> and a request to
            <literal>/index/welcome.html</literal> comes in, the
            <literal>doIt(HttpServletRequest, HttpServletResponse)</literal>
            method is called. This method name resolver works with the
            <literal>PathMatcher</literal>, so if the properties contained
            <literal>/**/welcom?.html</literal>, it would also have
            worked!</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist></para>

      <para>Here are a couple of examples. First, an example showing the
      <literal>ParameterMethodNameResolver</literal> and the delegate
      property, which will accept requests to urls with the parameter method
      included and set to <literal>retrieveIndex</literal>: <programlisting>&lt;bean id="paramResolver" class="org....mvc.multiaction.ParameterMethodNameResolver"&gt;
  &lt;property name="paramName"&gt;&lt;value&gt;method&lt;/value&gt;&lt;/property&gt;
&lt;/bean&gt;

&lt;bean id="paramMultiController" class="org....mvc.multiaction.MultiActionController"&gt;
  &lt;property name="methodNameResolver"&gt;&lt;ref bean="paramResolver"/&gt;&lt;/property&gt;
  &lt;property name="delegate"&gt;&lt;ref bean="sampleDelegate"/&gt;&lt;/property&gt;
&lt;/bean&gt;

&lt;bean id="sampleDelegate" class="samples.SampleDelegate"/&gt;

## together with

public class SampleDelegate {

    public ModelAndView retrieveIndex(
        HttpServletRequest req,
        HttpServletResponse resp) {

        return new ModelAndView("index", "date", new Long(System.currentTimeMillis()));
    }
}</programlisting> When using the delegates shown above, we could also use the
      <literal>PropertiesMethodNameResolver</literal> to match a couple of
      URLs to the method we defined: <programlisting>&lt;bean id="propsResolver" class="org....mvc.multiaction.PropertiesMethodNameResolver"&gt;
  &lt;property name="mappings"&gt;
    &lt;props&gt;
      &lt;prop key="/index/welcome.html"&gt;retrieveIndex&lt;/prop&gt;
      &lt;prop key="/**/notwelcome.html"&gt;retrieveIndex&lt;/prop&gt;
      &lt;prop key="/*/user?.html"&gt;retrieveIndex&lt;/prop&gt;
    &lt;/props&gt;
  &lt;/property&gt;
&lt;/bean&gt;

&lt;bean id="paramMultiController" class="org....mvc.multiaction.MultiActionController"&gt;
    &lt;property name="methodNameResolver"&gt;&lt;ref bean="propsResolver"/&gt;&lt;/property&gt;
    &lt;property name="delegate"&gt;&lt;ref bean="sampleDelegate"/&gt;&lt;/property&gt;
&lt;/bean&gt;</programlisting></para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="mvc-controller-command">
      <title>CommandControllers</title>

      <para>Spring's <emphasis>CommandControllers</emphasis> are a fundamental
      part of the Spring MVC package. Command controllers provide a way to
      interact with data objects and dynamically bind parameters from the
      <literal>HttpServletRequest</literal> to the data object specified. They
      perform a similar role to Struts' ActionForm, but in Spring, your data
      objects don't have to implement a framework-specific interface. First,
      let's examine what command controllers available, to get overview of
      what you can do with them: <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
          <listitem>
            <para><literal>AbstractCommandController</literal> - a command
            controller you can use to create your own command controller,
            capable of binding request parameters to a data object you
            specify. This class does not offer form functionality, it does
            however, offer validation features and lets you specify in the
            controller itself what to do with the command object that has been
            filled with the parameters from the request.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><literal>AbstractFormController</literal> - an abstract
            controller offering form submission support. Using this controller
            you can model forms and populate them using a command object you
            retrieve in the controller. After a user has filled the form, the
            AbstractFormController binds the fields, validates, and hands the
            object back to the controller to take appropriate action.
            Supported features are: invalid form submission (resubmission),
            validation, and normal form workflow. You implement methods to
            determine which views are used for form presentation and success.
            Use this controller if you need forms, but don't want to specify
            what views you're going to show the user in the application
            context.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><literal>SimpleFormController</literal> - a concrete
            FormController that provides even more support when creating a
            form with a corresponding command object. The SimpleFormController
            let's you specify a command object, a viewname for the form, a
            viewname for page you want to show the user when form submission
            has succeeded, and more.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><literal>AbstractWizardFormController</literal> - as the
            class name suggests, this is an abstract class--your
            WizardController should extend it. This means you have to
            implement the <literal>validatePage()</literal>,
            <literal>processFinish</literal> and
            <literal>processCancel</literal> methods.</para>

            <para>You probably also want to write a contractor, which should
            at the very least call <literal>setPages()</literal> and
            <literal>setCommandName()</literal>. The former takes as its
            argument an array of type String. This array is the list of views
            which comprise your wizard. The latter takes as its argument a
            String, which will be used to refer to your command object from
            within your views.</para>

            <para>As with any instance of AbstractFormController, you are
            required to use a command object - a JavaBean which will be
            populated with the data from your forms. You can do this in one of
            two ways: either call <literal>setCommandClass()</literal> from
            the constructor with the class of your command object, or
            implement the <literal>formBackingObject()</literal>
            method.</para>

            <para>AbstractWizardFormController has a number of concrete
            methods that you may wish to override. Of these, the ones you are
            likely to find most useful are: <literal>referenceData</literal>
            which you can use to pass model data to your view in the form of a
            Map; <literal>getTargetPage</literal> if your wizard needs to
            change page order or omit pages dynamically; and
            <literal>onBindAndValidate</literal> if you want to override the
            built-in binding and validation workflow.</para>

            <para>Finally, it is worth pointing out the
            <literal>setAllowDirtyBack</literal> and
            <literal>setAllowDirtyForward</literal>, which you can call from
            <literal>getTargetPage</literal> to allow users to move backwards
            and forwards in the wizard even if validation fails for the
            current page.</para>

            <para>For a full list of methods, see the JavaDoc for
            AbstractWizardFormController. There is an implemented example of
            this wizard in the jPetStore included in the Spring distribution:
            org.springframework.samples.jpetstore.web.spring.OrderFormController</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist></para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="mvc-handlermapping">
    <title>Handler mappings</title>

    <para>Using a handler mapping you can map incoming web requests to
    appropriate handlers. There are some handler mappings you can use out of
    the box, for example, the <literal>SimpleUrlHandlerMapping</literal> or
    the <literal>BeanNameUrlHandlerMapping</literal>, but let's first examine
    the general concept of a <literal>HandlerMapping</literal>.</para>

    <para>The functionality a basic <literal>HandlerMapping</literal> provides
    is the delivering of a <literal>HandlerExecutionChain</literal>, which
    must contain the handler that matches the incoming request, and may also
    contain a list of handler interceptors that are applied to the request.
    When a request comes in, the <literal>DispatcherServlet</literal> will
    hand it over to the handler mapping to let it inspect the request and come
    up with an appropriate HandlerExecutionChain. Then the DispatcherServlet
    will execute the handler and interceptors in the chain (if any).</para>

    <para>The concept of configurable handler mappings that can optionally
    contain interceptors (executed before or after the actual handler was
    executed, or both) is extremely powerful. A lot of supporting
    functionality can be built into custom <literal>HandlerMapping</literal>s.
    Think of a custom handler mapping that chooses a handler not only based on
    the URL of the request coming in, but also on a specific state of the
    session associated with the request.</para>

    <para>This section describes two of Spring's most commonly used handler
    mappings. They both extend the <literal>AbstractHandlerMapping</literal>
    and share the following properties: <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para><literal>interceptors</literal>: the list of interceptors to
          use. <literal>HandlerInterceptor</literal>s are discussed in <xref
          linkend="mvc-handlermapping-interceptor" />.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><literal>defaultHandler</literal>: the default handler to use,
          when this handler mapping does not result in a matching
          handler.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><literal>order</literal>: based on the value of the order
          property (see the
          <literal>org.springframework.core.Ordered</literal> interface),
          Spring will sort all handler mappings available in the context and
          apply the first matching handler.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><literal>alwaysUseFullPath</literal>: if this property is set
          to <literal>true</literal>, Spring will use the full path within the
          current servlet context to find an appropriate handler. If this
          property is set to <literal>false</literal> (the default), the path
          within the current servlet mapping will be used. For example, if a
          servlet is mapped using <literal>/testing/*</literal> and the
          <literal>alwaysUseFullPath</literal> property is set to true,
          <literal>/testing/viewPage.html</literal> would be used, whereas if
          the property is set to false, <literal>/viewPage.html</literal>
          would be used.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><literal>urlPathHelper</literal>: using this property, you can
          tweak the UrlPathHelper used when inspecting URLs. Normally, you
          shouldn't have to change the default value.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><literal>urlDecode</literal>: the default value for this
          property is <literal>false</literal>. The
          <literal>HttpServletRequest</literal> returns request URLs and URIs
          that are <emphasis>not</emphasis> decoded. If you do want them to be
          decoded before a <literal>HandlerMapping</literal> uses them to find
          an appropriate handler, you have to set this to
          <literal>true</literal> (note that this requires JDK 1.4). The
          decoding method uses either the encoding specified by the request or
          the default ISO-8859-1 encoding scheme.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><literal>lazyInitHandlers</literal>: allows for lazy
          initialization of <emphasis>singleton</emphasis> handlers (prototype
          handlers are always lazily initialized). Default value is
          <literal>false</literal>.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist> (<emphasis>Note: the last four properties are only
    available to subclasses of
    <literal>org.springframework.web.servlet.handler.AbstractUrlHandlerMapping</literal></emphasis>).</para>

    <sect2 id="mvc-handlermapping-beanname">
      <title><literal>BeanNameUrlHandlerMapping</literal></title>

      <para>A very simple, but very powerful handler mapping is the
      <literal>BeanNameUrlHandlerMapping</literal>, which maps incoming HTTP
      requests to names of beans, defined in the web application context.
      Let's say we want to enable a user to insert an account and we've
      already provided an appropriate FormController (see <xref
      linkend="mvc-controller-command" /> for more information on Command- and
      FormControllers) and a JSP view (or Velocity template) that renders the
      form. When using the BeanNameUrlHandlerMapping, we could map the HTTP
      request with URL <literal>http://samples.com/editaccount.form</literal>
      to the appropriate FormController as follows: <programlisting>&lt;beans&gt;
  &lt;bean id="handlerMapping" class="org.springframework.web.servlet.handler.BeanNameUrlHandlerMapping"/&gt;

  &lt;bean name="/editaccount.form" class="org.springframework.web.servlet.mvc.SimpleFormController"&gt;
    &lt;property name="formView"&gt;&lt;value&gt;account&lt;/value&gt;&lt;/property&gt;
    &lt;property name="successView"&gt;&lt;value&gt;account-created&lt;/value&gt;&lt;/property&gt;
    &lt;property name="commandName"&gt;&lt;value&gt;Account&lt;/value&gt;&lt;/property&gt;
    &lt;property name="commandClass"&gt;&lt;value&gt;samples.Account&lt;/value&gt;&lt;/property&gt;
  &lt;/bean&gt;
&lt;beans&gt;    </programlisting> All incoming requests for the URL
      <literal>/editaccount.form</literal> will now be handled by the
      FormController in the source listing above. Of course we have to define
      a servlet-mapping in web.xml as well, to let through all the requests
      ending with .form. <programlisting>&lt;web-app&gt;
    ...
    &lt;servlet&gt;
        &lt;servlet-name&gt;sample&lt;/servlet-name&gt;
        &lt;servlet-class&gt;org.springframework.web.servlet.DispatcherServlet&lt;/servlet-class&gt;
        &lt;load-on-startup&gt;1&lt;/load-on-startup&gt;
    &lt;/servlet&gt;

   &lt;!-- Maps the sample dispatcher to /*.form --&gt;
    &lt;servlet-mapping&gt;
        &lt;servlet-name&gt;sample&lt;/servlet-name&gt;
        &lt;url-pattern&gt;*.form&lt;/url-pattern&gt;
    &lt;/servlet-mapping&gt;
    ...
&lt;/web-app&gt;</programlisting></para>

      <para><emphasis>NOTE: if you want to use the
      <literal>BeanNameUrlHandlerMapping</literal>, you don't necessarily have
      to define it in the web application context (as indicated above). By
      default, if no handler mapping can be found in the context, the
      DispatcherServlet creates a <literal>BeanNameUrlHandlerMapping</literal>
      for you! </emphasis></para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="mvc-handlermapping-urlhandlermapping">
      <title><literal>SimpleUrlHandlerMapping</literal></title>

      <para>A further - and much more powerful handler mapping - is the
      <literal>SimpleUrlHandlerMapping</literal>. This mapping is configurable
      in the application context and has Ant-style path matching capabilities
      (see the JavaDoc for
      <literal>org.springframework.util.PathMatcher</literal>). Here is an
      example: <programlisting>&lt;web-app&gt;
    ...
    &lt;servlet&gt;
        &lt;servlet-name&gt;sample&lt;/servlet-name&gt;
        &lt;servlet-class&gt;org.springframework.web.servlet.DispatcherServlet&lt;/servlet-class&gt;
        &lt;load-on-startup&gt;1&lt;/load-on-startup&gt;
    &lt;/servlet&gt;

    &lt;!-- Maps the sample dispatcher to /*.form --&gt;
    &lt;servlet-mapping&gt;
        &lt;servlet-name&gt;sample&lt;/servlet-name&gt;
        &lt;url-pattern&gt;*.form&lt;/url-pattern&gt;
    &lt;/servlet-mapping&gt;
    &lt;servlet-mapping&gt;
        &lt;servlet-name&gt;sample&lt;/servlet-name&gt;
        &lt;url-pattern&gt;*.html&lt;/url-pattern&gt;
    &lt;/servlet-mapping&gt;
    ...
&lt;/web-app&gt;</programlisting> Allows all requests ending with .html and
      .form to be handled by the sample dispatcher servlet. <programlisting>&lt;beans&gt;
    &lt;bean id="handlerMapping"
          class="org.springframework.web.servlet.handler.SimpleUrlHandlerMapping"&gt;
        &lt;property name="mappings"&gt;
            &lt;props&gt;
                &lt;prop key="/*/account.form"&gt;editAccountFormController&lt;/prop&gt;
                &lt;prop key="/*/editaccount.form"&gt;editAccountFormController&lt;/prop&gt;
                &lt;prop key="/ex/view*.html"&gt;someViewController&lt;/prop&gt;
                &lt;prop key="/**/help.html"&gt;helpController&lt;/prop&gt;
            &lt;/props&gt;
        &lt;/property&gt;
    &lt;/bean&gt;

    &lt;bean id="someViewController"
          class="org.springframework.web.servlet.mvc.UrlFilenameViewController"/&gt;

    &lt;bean id="editAccountFormController"
          class="org.springframework.web.servlet.mvc.SimpleFormController"&gt;
        &lt;property name="formView"&gt;&lt;value&gt;account&lt;/value&gt;&lt;/property&gt;
        &lt;property name="successView"&gt;&lt;value&gt;account-created&lt;/value&gt;&lt;/property&gt;
        &lt;property name="commandName"&gt;&lt;value&gt;Account&lt;/value&gt;&lt;/property&gt;
        &lt;property name="commandClass"&gt;&lt;value&gt;samples.Account&lt;/value&gt;&lt;/property&gt;
    &lt;/bean&gt;
&lt;beans&gt;</programlisting> This handler mapping routes requests for
      <literal>help.html</literal> in any directory to the
      <literal>helpController</literal>, which is a UrlFilenameViewController
      (more about controllers can be found in <xref
      linkend="mvc-controller" />). Requests for a resource beginning with
      <literal>view</literal>, and ending with <literal>.html</literal> in the
      directory <literal>ex</literal>, will be routed to the
      <literal>someViewController</literal>. Two further mappings are defined
      for <literal>editAccountFormController</literal>.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="mvc-handlermapping-interceptor">
      <title>Adding <literal>HandlerInterceptors</literal></title>

      <para>Spring's handler mapping mechanism has a notion of handler
      interceptors, that can be extremely useful when you want to apply
      specific functionality to certain requests, for example, checking for a
      principal.</para>

      <para>Interceptors located in the handler mapping must implement
      <literal>HandlerInterceptor</literal> from the
      <literal>org.springframework.web.servlet</literal> package. This
      interface defines three methods, one that will be called
      <emphasis>before</emphasis> the actual handler will be executed, one
      that will be called <emphasis>after</emphasis> the handler is executed,
      and one that is called <emphasis>after the complete request has
      finished</emphasis>. These three methods should provide enough
      flexibility to do all kinds of pre- and post-processing.</para>

      <para>The <literal>preHandle</literal> method returns a boolean value.
      You can use this method to break or continue the processing of the
      execution chain. When this method returns <literal>true</literal>, the
      handler execution chain will continue, when it returns false, the
      DispatcherServlet assumes the interceptor itself has taken care of
      requests (and, for example, rendered an appropriate view) and does not
      continue executing the other interceptors and the actual handler in the
      execution chain.</para>

      <para>The following example provides an interceptor that intercepts all
      requests and reroutes the user to a specific page if the time is not
      between 9 a.m. and 6 p.m. <programlisting>&lt;beans&gt;
    &lt;bean id="handlerMapping"
          class="org.springframework.web.servlet.handler.SimpleUrlHandlerMapping"&gt;
        &lt;property name="interceptors"&gt;
            &lt;list&gt;
                &lt;ref bean="officeHoursInterceptor"/&gt;
            &lt;/list&gt;
        &lt;/property&gt;
        &lt;property name="mappings"&gt;
            &lt;props&gt;
                &lt;prop key="/*.form"&gt;editAccountFormController&lt;/prop&gt;
                &lt;prop key="/*.view"&gt;editAccountFormController&lt;/prop&gt;
            &lt;/props&gt;
        &lt;/property&gt;
    &lt;/bean&gt;

    &lt;bean id="officeHoursInterceptor"
          class="samples.TimeBasedAccessInterceptor"&gt;
        &lt;property name="openingTime"&gt;&lt;value&gt;9&lt;/value&gt;&lt;/property&gt;
        &lt;property name="closingTime"&gt;&lt;value&gt;18&lt;/value&gt;&lt;/property&gt;
    &lt;/bean&gt;
&lt;beans&gt;</programlisting> <programlisting>package samples;

public class TimeBasedAccessInterceptor extends HandlerInterceptorAdapter {

    private int openingTime;
    private int closingTime;
    public void setOpeningTime(int openingTime) {
        this.openingTime = openingTime;
    }
    public void setClosingTime(int closingTime) {
        this.closingTime = closingTime;
    }
    public boolean preHandle(
            HttpServletRequest request,
            HttpServletResponse response,
            Object handler)
    throws Exception {
        Calendar cal = Calendar.getInstance();
        int hour = cal.get(HOUR_OF_DAY);
        if (openingTime &lt;= hour &lt; closingTime) {
            return true;
        } else {
            response.sendRedirect("http://host.com/outsideOfficeHours.html");
            return false;
        }
    }
}</programlisting> Any request coming in, will be intercepted by the
      <literal>TimeBasedAccessInterceptor</literal>, and if the current time
      is outside office hours, the user will be redirected to a static html
      file, saying, for example, he can only access the website during office
      hours.</para>

      <para>As you can see, Spring has an adapter to make it easy for you to
      extend the <literal>HandlerInterceptor</literal>.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

     <sect1 id="mvc-viewresolver">
       <title>Views and resolving them</title>

    <para>All MVC frameworks for web applications provide a way to address
    views. Spring provides view resolvers, which enable you to render models
    in a browser without tying you to a specific view technology. Out of the
    box, Spring enables you to use Java Server Pages, Velocity templates and
    XSLT views, for example. <xref linkend="view" /> has details of
    integrating various view technologies.</para>

    <para>The two interfaces which are important to the way Spring handles
    views are <literal>ViewResolver</literal> and <literal>View</literal>. The
    <literal>ViewResolver</literal> provides a mapping between view names and
    actual views. The <literal>View</literal> interface addresses the
    preparation of the request and hands the request over to one of the view
    technologies.</para>

    <sect2 id="mvc-viewresolver-resolver">
      <title>ViewResolvers</title>

      <para>As discussed in <xref linkend="mvc-controller" />, all controllers
      in the Spring web MVC framework, return a
      <literal>ModelAndView</literal> instance. Views in Spring are addressed
      by a view name and are resolved by a view resolver. Spring comes with
      quite a few view resolvers. We'll list most of them and then provide a
      couple of examples.</para>

      <table frame="all">
        <title>View resolvers</title>

        <tgroup cols="2">
          <colspec colname="c1" colwidth="1*" />

          <colspec colname="c2" colwidth="2*" />

          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>ViewResolver</entry>

              <entry>Description</entry>
            </row>
          </thead>

          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>AbstractCachingViewResolver</entry>

              <entry>An abstract view resolver which takes care of caching
              views. Often views need preparation before they can be used,
              extending this view resolver provides caching of views.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>XmlViewResolver</entry>

              <entry>An implementation of ViewResolver that accepts a
              configuration file written in XML with the same DTD as Spring's
              bean factories. The default configuration file is
              <literal>/WEB-INF/views.xml</literal>.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>ResourceBundleViewResolver</entry>

              <entry>An implementation of ViewResolver that uses bean
              definitions in a ResourceBundle, specified by the bundle
              basename. The bundle is typically defined in a properties file,
              located in the classpath. The default file name is
              <literal>views.properties</literal>.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>UrlBasedViewResolver</entry>

              <entry>A simple implementation of ViewResolver that allows for
              direct resolution of symbolic view names to URLs, without an
              explicit mapping definition. This is appropriate if your
              symbolic names match the names of your view resources in a
              straightforward manner, without the need for arbitrary
              mappings.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>InternalResourceViewResolver</entry>

              <entry>A convenience subclass of UrlBasedViewResolver that
              supports InternalResourceView (i.e. Servlets and JSPs), and
              subclasses like JstlView and TilesView. The view class for all
              views generated by this resolver can be specified via
              setViewClass. See UrlBasedViewResolver's javadocs for
              details.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>VelocityViewResolver / FreeMarkerViewResolver</entry>

              <entry>A convenience subclass of UrlBasedViewResolver that
              supports VelocityView (i.e. Velocity templates) or
              FreeMarkerView respectively and custom subclasses of
              them.</entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>

      <para>As an example, when using JSP for a view technology you can use
      the <literal>UrlBasedViewResolver</literal>. This view resolver
      translates a view name to a URL and hands the request over the
      RequestDispatcher to render the view. <programlisting>&lt;bean id="viewResolver"
      class="org.springframework.web.servlet.view.UrlBasedViewResolver"&gt;
    &lt;property name="prefix"&gt;&lt;value&gt;/WEB-INF/jsp/&lt;/value&gt;&lt;/property&gt;
    &lt;property name="suffix"&gt;&lt;value&gt;.jsp&lt;/value&gt;&lt;/property&gt;
&lt;/bean&gt;</programlisting> When returning <literal>test</literal> as a
      viewname, this view resolver will hand the request over to the
      RequestDispatcher that will send the request to
      <literal>/WEB-INF/jsp/test.jsp</literal>.</para>

      <para>When mixing different view technologies in a web application, you
      can use the ResourceBundleViewResolver: <programlisting>&lt;bean id="viewResolver"
      class="org.springframework.web.servlet.view.ResourceBundleViewResolver"&gt;
    &lt;property name="basename"&gt;&lt;value&gt;views&lt;/value&gt;&lt;/property&gt;
    &lt;property name="defaultParentView"&gt;&lt;value&gt;parentView&lt;/value&gt;&lt;/property&gt;
&lt;/bean&gt;</programlisting></para>

      <para>The ResourceBundleViewResolver inspects the ResourceBundle
      identified by the basename, and for each view it is supposed to resolve,
      it uses the value of the property <literal>[viewname].class</literal> as
      the view class and the value of the property
      <literal>[viewname].url</literal> as the view url. As you can see, you
      can identify a parent view, from which all views in the properties file
      sort of extend. This way you can specify a default view class, for
      example.</para>

      <para><emphasis>A note on caching</emphasis> - subclasses of
      <literal>AbstractCachingViewResolver</literal> cache view instances they
      have resolved. This greatly improves performance when using certain view
      technology. It's possible to turn off the cache, by setting the
      <literal>cache</literal> property to false. Furthermore, if you have the
      requirement to be able to refresh a certain view at runtime (for example
      when a Velocity template has been modified), you can use the
      <literal>removeFromCache(String viewName, Locale loc)</literal>
      method.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="mvc-viewresolver-chaining">
      <title>Chaining ViewResolvers</title>

      <para>Spring supports more than just one view resolver. This allows you
      to chain resolvers and, for example, override specific views in certain
      circumstances. Chaining view resolvers is pretty straightforward - just
      add more than one resolver to your application context and, if
      necessary, set the <literal>order</literal> property to specify an
      order. Remember, the higher the order property, the later the view
      resolver will be positioned in the chain.</para>

      <para>In the following example, the chain of view resolvers consists of
      two resolvers, a <literal>InternalResourceViewResolver</literal> (which
      is always automatically positioned as the last resolver in the chain)
      and an <literal>XmlViewResolver</literal> for specifying Excel views
      (which are not supported by the InternalResourceViewResolver):
      <programlisting>
&lt;bean id="jspViewResolver" class="org.springframework.web.servlet.view.InternalResourceViewResolver"&gt;
  &lt;property name="viewClass" value="org.springframework.web.servlet.view.JstlView"/&gt;
  &lt;property name="prefix" value="/WEB-INF/jsp/"/&gt;
  &lt;property name="suffix" value=".jsp"/&gt;
&lt;/bean&gt;

&lt;bean id="excelViewResolver" class="org.springframework.web.servlet.view.XmlViewResolver"&gt;
  &lt;property name="order" value="1"/&gt;
  &lt;property name="location" value="/WEB-INF/views.xml"/&gt;
&lt;/bean&gt;

### views.xml

&lt;beans&gt;
  &lt;bean name="report" class="org.springframework.example.ReportExcelView"/&gt;
&lt;/beans&gt;
</programlisting></para>

      <para>If a specific view resolver does not result in a view, Spring will
      inspect the context to see if other view resolvers are configured. If
      there are additional view resolvers, it will continue to inspect them.
      If not, it will throw an Exception.</para>

      <para>You have to keep something else in mind - the contract of a view
      resolver mentions that a view resolver <emphasis>can</emphasis> return
      null to indicate the view could not be found. Not all view resolvers do
      this however! This is because in some cases, the resolver simply cannot
      detect whether or not the view exists. For example, the
      <literal>InternalResourceViewResolver</literal> uses the
      RequestDispatcher internally, and dispatching is the only way to figure
      out if a JSP exists -this can only be done once. The same holds for the
      VelocityViewResolver and some others. Check the JavaDoc for the view
      resolver to see if you're dealing with a view resolver that does not
      report non-existing views. As a result of this, putting an
      <literal>InternalResourceViewResolver</literal> in the chain in a place
      other than the last, will result in the chain not being fully inspected,
      since the <literal>InternalResourceViewResolver</literal> will
      <emphasis>always</emphasis> return a view!</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Redirecting to views</title>

      <para>As has been mentioned, a controller normally returns a logical
      view name, which a view resolver resolves to a particular view
      technology. For view tehcnologies such as JSPs that are actually
      processed via the Servlet/JSP engine, this is normally handled via
      <literal>InternalResourceViewResolver</literal>/<literal>InternalResourceView</literal>
      which will ultimately end up issuing an internal forward or include, via
      the Servlet API's <literal>RequestDispatcher.forward()</literal> or
      <literal>RequestDispatcher.include()</literal>. For other view
      technologies, such as Velocity, XSLT, etc., the view itself produces the
      content on the response stream.</para>

      <para>It is sometimes desirable to issue an HTTP redirect back to the
      client, before the view is rendered. This is desirable for example when
      one controller has been called with POSTed data, and the response is
      actually a delegation to another controller (for example on a successful
      form submission). In this case, a normal internal forward will mean the
      other controller will also see the same POST data, whih is potentially
      problematic if it can confuse it with other expected data Another reason
      to do a redirect before displaying the result is that this will
      eliminate the possiblity of the user doing a double submission of form
      data. The browser will have sent the initial POST, will have seen a
      redirect back and done a subsequent GET because of that, and thus as far
      as it is concerned, the current page does not reflect the result of a
      POST, but rather of a GET, so there is no way the user can accidentally
      re-POST the same data by doing a refresh. The refresh would just force a
      GET of the result page, not a resend of the initial POST data.</para>

      <sect3>
        <title><literal>RedirectView</literal></title>

        <para>One way to force a redirect as the result of a controller
        response is for the controller to create and return an instance of
        Spring's <literal>RedirectView</literal>. In this case,
        <literal>DispatcherServlet</literal> will not use the normal view
        resolution mechanism, but rather as it has been given the (redirect)
        view already, will just ask it to do it's work.</para>

        <para>The <literal>RedirectView</literal> simply ends up issuing an
        <literal>HttpServletResponse.sendRedirect()</literal> call, which will
        come back to the client browser as an HTTP redirect. All model
        attributes are simply exposed as HTTP query parameters. This does mean
        that the model must contain only objects (generally Strings or
        convertible to Strings) which can be readily converted to a
        string-form HTTP query parameter.</para>

        <para>If using RedirectView, and the view is created by the Controller
        itself, it is generally always preferable if the redirect URL at least
        is injected into the Controller, so that it is not baked into the
        controller but rather configured in the context along with view names
        and the like.</para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>The <literal>redirect:</literal> prefix</title>

        <para>While the use of <literal>RedirectView</literal> works fine, if
        the controller itself is creating the <literal>RedirectView</literal>,
        there is no getting around the fact that the controller is aware that
        a redirection is happening. This is really suboptimal and couples
        things too tightly. The controller should not really care about how
        the response gets handled. It should generally think only in terms of
        view names, that have been injected into it.</para>

        <para>The special redirect: prefix allows this to be achived. If a
        view name is returned which has the prefix redirect:, then
        <literal>UrlBasedViewResolver</literal> (and all subclasses) will
        recognize this as a special indication that a redirect is needed. The
        rest of the view name will be treated as the redirect URL.</para>

        <para>The net effect is the same as if the controller had returned a
        <literal>RedirectView</literal>, but now the controller itself can
        deal just in terms of logical view names. A logical view name such as
        <literal>redirect:/my/response/controller.html</literal> will redirect
        relative to the current servlet context, while a name such as
        <literal>redirect:http://myhost.com/some/arbitrary/path.html</literal>
        will redirect to an absolute URL. The important thing is that as long
        is this redirect view name is injected into the controller like any
        other logical view name, the controller is not even aware that
        redirection is happening.</para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>The <literal>forward:</literal> prefix</title>

        <para>It is also possible to use a special forward: prefix for view
        names that will ultimately be resolved by
        <literal>UrlBasedViewResolver</literal> and subclasses. All this does
        is create an <literal>InternalResourceView</literal> (which ultimately
        does a <literal>RequestDispatcher.forward()</literal>) around the rest
        of the view name, which is considered a URL. Therefore, there is never
        any use in using this prefix when using
        <literal>InternalResourceViewResolver</literal>/<literal>InternalResourceView</literal>
        anyway (for JSPs for example), but it's of potential use when you are
        primarilly using another view technology, but want to still be able to
        in some cases force a forward to happen to a resource to be handled by
        the Servlet/JSP engine. Note that if you need to do this a lot though,
        you may also just chain multiple view resolvers.</para>

        <para>As with the <literal>redirect:</literal> prefix, if the view
        name with the prefix is just injected into the controller, the
        controller does not have to be aware that anything special is
        happening in terms of handling the response.</para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="mvc-localeresolver">
    <title>Using locales</title>

    <para>Most parts of Spring's architecture support internationalization,
    just as the Spring web MVC framework does. DispatcherServlet enables you
    to automatically resolve messages using the client's locale. This is done
    with <literal>LocaleResolver</literal> objects.</para>

    <para>When a request comes in, the DispatcherServlet looks for a locale
    resolver and if it finds one it tries to use it to set the locale. Using
    the <literal>RequestContext.getLocale()</literal> method, you can always
    retrieve the locale that was resolved by the locale resolver.</para>

    <para>Besides the automatic locale resolution, you can also attach an
    interceptor to the handler mapping (see <xref
    linkend="mvc-handlermapping-interceptor" /> for more information on
    handler mapping interceptors), to change the locale under specific
    circumstances, based on a parameter in the request, for example.</para>

    <para>Locale resolvers and interceptors are all defined in the
    <literal>org.springframework.web.servlet.i18n</literal> package, and are
    configured in your application context in the normal way. Here is a
    selection of the locale resolvers included in Spring.</para>

    <sect2 id="mvc-localeresolver-acceptheader">
      <title><literal>AcceptHeaderLocaleResolver</literal></title>

      <para>This locale resolver inspects the
      <literal>accept-language</literal> header in the request that was sent
      by the browser of the client. Usually this header field contains the
      locale of the client's operating system.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="mvc-localeresolver-cookie">
      <title><literal>CookieLocaleResolver</literal></title>

      <para>This locale resolver inspects a Cookie that might exist on the
      client, to see if a locale is specified. If so, it uses that specific
      locale. Using the properties of this locale resolver, you can specify
      the name of the cookie, as well as the maximum age. <programlisting>&lt;bean id="localeResolver"&gt;
    &lt;property name="cookieName"&gt;&lt;value&gt;clientlanguage&lt;/value&gt;&lt;/property&gt;
    &lt;!-- in seconds. If set to -1, the cookie is not persisted (deleted when browser shuts down) --&gt;
    &lt;property name="cookieMaxAge"&gt;&lt;value&gt;100000&lt;/value&gt;&lt;/property&gt;
&lt;/bean&gt;</programlisting> This is an example of defining a
      CookieLocaleResolver.</para>

      <table frame="all">
        <title>Special beans in the WebApplicationContext</title>

        <tgroup cols="3">
          <colspec colname="c1" colwidth="1*" />

          <colspec colname="c2" colwidth="1*" />

          <colspec colname="c3" colwidth="3*" />

          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>Property</entry>

              <entry>Default</entry>

              <entry>Description</entry>
            </row>
          </thead>

          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>cookieName</entry>

              <entry>classname + LOCALE</entry>

              <entry>The name of the cookie</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>cookieMaxAge</entry>

              <entry>Integer.MAX_INT</entry>

              <entry>The maximum time a cookie will stay persistent on the
              client. If -1 is specified, the cookie will not be persisted. It
              will only be available until the client shuts down his or her
              browser.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>cookiePath</entry>

              <entry>/</entry>

              <entry>Using this parameter, you can limit the visibility of the
              cookie to a certain part of your site. When cookiePath is
              specified, the cookie will only be visible to that path, and the
              paths below it.</entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="mvc-localeresolver-session">
      <title><literal>SessionLocaleResolver</literal></title>

      <para>The <literal>SessionLocaleResolver</literal> allows you to
      retrieve locales from the session that might be associated with the
      user's request.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="mvc-localeresolver-interceptor">
      <title><literal>LocaleChangeInterceptor</literal></title>

      <para>You can build in changing of locales using the
      <literal>LocaleChangeInterceptor</literal>. This interceptor needs to be
      added to one of the handler mappings (see <xref
      linkend="mvc-handlermapping" />). It will detect a parameter in the
      request and change the locale (it calls <literal>setLocale()</literal>
      on the LocaleResolver that also exists in the context). <programlisting>&lt;bean id="localeChangeInterceptor"
      class="org.springframework.web.servlet.i18n.LocaleChangeInterceptor"&gt;
    &lt;property name="paramName"&gt;&lt;value&gt;siteLanguage&lt;/value&gt;&lt;/property&gt;
&lt;/bean&gt;

&lt;bean id="localeResolver"
      class="org.springframework.web.servlet.i18n.CookieLocaleResolver"/&gt;

&lt;bean id="urlMapping"
      class="org.springframework.web.servlet.handler.SimpleUrlHandlerMapping"&gt;
    &lt;property name="interceptors"&gt;
        &lt;list&gt;
            &lt;ref bean="localeChangeInterceptor"/&gt;
        &lt;/list&gt;
    &lt;/property&gt;
    &lt;property name="mappings"&gt;
        &lt;props&gt;
            &lt;prop key="/**/*.view"&gt;someController&lt;/prop&gt;
        &lt;/props&gt;
    &lt;/property&gt;
&lt;/bean&gt;</programlisting> All calls to all *.view resources containing a
      parameter named <literal>siteLanguage</literal> will now change the
      locale. So a call to
      <literal>http://www.sf.net/home.view?siteLanguage=nl</literal> will
      change the site language to Dutch.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="mvc-themeresolver">
    <title>Using themes</title>

    <sect2 id="mvc-themeresolver-introduction">
      <title>Introduction</title>

      <para>The <emphasis>theme</emphasis> support provided by the Spring web
      MVC framework enables you to further enhance the user experience by
      allowing the look and feel of your application to be
      <emphasis>themed</emphasis>. A theme is basically a collection of static
      resources affecting the visual style of the application, typically style
      sheets and images.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="mvc-themeresolver-defining">
      <title>Defining themes</title>

      <para>When you want to use themes in your web application you'll have to
      setup a <literal>org.springframework.ui.context.ThemeSource</literal>.
      The <literal>WebApplicationContext</literal> interface extends
      <literal>ThemeSource</literal> but delegates its responsabilities to a
      dedicated implementation. By default the delegate will be a
      <literal>org.springframework.ui.context.support.ResourceBundleThemeSource</literal>
      that loads properties files from the root of the classpath. If you want
      to use a custom <literal>ThemeSource</literal> implementation or if you
      need to configure the basename prefix of the
      <literal>ResourceBundleThemeSource</literal>, you can register a bean in
      the application context with the reserved name "themeSource". The web
      application context will automatically detect that bean and start using
      it.</para>

      <para>When using the <literal>ResourceBundleThemeSource</literal>, a
      theme is defined in a simple properties file. The properties file lists
      the resources that make up the theme. Here's an example:
      <programlisting>styleSheet=/themes/cool/style.css
background=/themes/cool/img/coolBg.jpg
</programlisting> The keys of the properties are the names used to refer to
      the themed elements from view code. For a JSP this would typically be
      done using the <literal>spring:theme</literal> custom tag, which is very
      similar to the <literal>spring:message</literal> tag. The following JSP
      fragment uses the theme defined above to customize the look and feel:
      <programlisting>&lt;taglib prefix="spring" uri="http://www.springframework.org/tags"%&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
   &lt;head&gt;
      &lt;link rel="stylesheet" href="&lt;spring:theme code="styleSheet"/&gt;" type="text/css"/&gt;
   &lt;/head&gt;
   &lt;body background="&lt;spring:theme code="background"/&gt;"&gt;
      ...
   &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;
</programlisting></para>

      <para>By default, the <literal>ResourceBundleThemeSource</literal> uses
      an empty basename prefix. As a result the properties files will be
      loaded from the root of the classpath, so we'll have to put our
      <literal>cool.properties</literal> theme definition in a directory at
      the root of the classpath, e.g. in <literal>/WEB-INF/classes</literal>.
      Note that the <literal>ResourceBundleThemeSource</literal> uses the
      standard Java resource bundle loading mechanism, allowing for full
      internationalisation of themes. For instance, we could have a
      <literal>/WEB-INF/classes/cool_nl.properties</literal> that references a
      special background image, e.g. with Dutch text on it.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="mvc-themeresolver-resolving">
      <title>Theme resolvers</title>

      <para>Now that we have our themes defined, the only thing left to do is
      decide which theme to use. The <literal>DispatcherServlet</literal> will
      look for a bean named "themeResolver" to find out which
      <literal>ThemeResolver</literal> implementation to use. A theme resolver
      works in much the same way as a <literal>LocalResolver</literal>. It can
      detect the theme that should be used for a particular request and can
      also alter the request's theme. The following theme resolvers are
      provided by Spring:</para>

      <table frame="all">
        <title>ThemeResolver implementations</title>

        <tgroup cols="2">
          <colspec colname="c1" colwidth="1*" />

          <colspec colname="c3" colwidth="3*" />

          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>Class</entry>

              <entry>Description</entry>
            </row>
          </thead>

          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>FixedThemeResolver</entry>

              <entry>Selects a fixed theme, set using the "defaultThemeName"
              property.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>SessionThemeResolver</entry>

              <entry>The theme is maintained in the users HTTP session. It
              only needs to be set once for each session, but is not persisted
              between sessions.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>CookieThemeResolver</entry>

              <entry>The selected theme is stored in a cookie on the client's
              machine.</entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>

      <para>Spring also provides a <literal>ThemeChangeInterceptor</literal>,
      which allows changing the theme on every request by including a simple
      request parameter.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <section id="mvc-multipart">
    <title>Spring's multipart (fileupload) support</title>
    <section id="mvc-multipart-introduction">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <para>
			Spring has built-in multipart support to handle fileuploads in web
			applications. The design for the multipart support is done with
			pluggable <interfacename>MultipartResolver</interfacename> objects,
			defined in the <literal>org.springframework.web.multipart</literal>
			package. Out of the	box, Spring provides
			<interfacename>MultipartResolver</interfacename>s for use with
			<emphasis>Commons FileUpload</emphasis>
			(<ulink	url="http://jakarta.apache.org/commons/fileupload"></ulink>) and
			<emphasis>COS FileUpload</emphasis>
			(<ulink	url="http://www.servlets.com/cos"></ulink>). How uploading
			files is supported will be described in the rest of this chapter.
      </para>
      <para>
			By default, no multipart handling will be done by Spring, as some
			developers will want to handle multiparts themselves. You will have to
			enable it yourself by adding a multipart resolver to the web
			application's context. After you have done that, each request will be
			inspected to see if it contains a multipart. If no multipart is found,
			the request will continue as expected. However, if a multipart is found
			in the request, the <classname>MultipartResolver</classname> that has
			been declared in your context will be used. After that, the multipart
			attribute in your request will be treated like any other attribute.
		</para>
    </section>

    <section id="mvc-multipart-resolver">
      <title>Using the <interfacename>MultipartResolver</interfacename></title>
      <para>
			The following example shows how to use the <classname>CommonsMultipartResolver</classname>:
      </para>
      <programlisting><![CDATA[<bean id="multipartResolver"
    class="org.springframework.web.multipart.commons.CommonsMultipartResolver">

    <!-- one of the properties available; the maximum file size in bytes -->
    <property name="maxUploadSize" value="100000"/>
</bean>]]></programlisting>
	  <para>
			This is an example using the <classname>CosMultipartResolver</classname>:
	  </para>
	  <programlisting><![CDATA[<bean id="multipartResolver" class="org.springframework.web.multipart.cos.CosMultipartResolver">

    <!-- one of the properties available; the maximum file size in bytes -->
    <property name="maxUploadSize" value="100000"/>
</bean>]]></programlisting>
      <para>
			Of course you also need to put the appropriate jars in your classpath
			for the multipart resolver to work. In the case of the
			<classname>CommonsMultipartResolver</classname>, you need to use
			<literal>commons-fileupload.jar</literal>; in the case of the
			<classname>CosMultipartResolver</classname>, use <literal>cos.jar</literal>.
	  </para>
      <para>
			Now that you have seen how to set Spring up to handle multipart
			requests, let's talk about how to actually use it. When the Spring
			<classname>DispatcherServlet</classname> detects a multi-part request,
			it activates the resolver that has been declared in your context and
			hands over the request. What the resolver then does is wrap the current
			<classname>HttpServletRequest</classname> into a
			<classname>MultipartHttpServletRequest</classname> that has support for
			multipart file uploads. Using the <classname>MultipartHttpServletRequest</classname>
			you can get information about the multiparts contained by this request
			and actually get access to the multipart files themselves in your controllers.
		</para>
    </section>

    <section id="mvc-multipart-forms">
      <title>Handling a file upload in a form</title>
      <para>
			After the <classname>MultipartResolver</classname> has finished doing its
			job, the request will be processed like any other. To use it, you create a form
			with an upload field (see immediately below), then let Spring bind the file
			onto your form (backing object). To actually let the user upload a file, we
			have to create a (HTML) form:
      </para>
      <programlisting><![CDATA[<html>
    <head>
        <title>Upload a file please</title>
    </head>
    <body>
        <h1>Please upload a file</h1>
        <form method="post" action="upload.form" enctype="multipart/form-data">
            <input type="file" name="file"/>
            <input type="submit"/>
        </form>
    </body>
</html>]]></programlisting>
        <para>
			As you can see, we've created a field named after the property of the bean
			that holds the <literal>byte[]</literal>. Furthermore we've added the
			encoding attribute (<literal>enctype="multipart/form-data"</literal>) which is
			necessary to let the browser know how to encode the multipart fields (do not
			forget this!).
		</para>
	  <para>
			Just as with any other property that's not automagically convertible to a
			string or primitive type, to be able to put binary data in your objects
			you have to register a custom editor with the
			<classname>ServletRequestDatabinder</classname>. There are a couple of
			editors available for handling files and setting the results on an object.
			There's a <classname>StringMultipartEditor</classname> capable of converting
			files to Strings (using a user-defined character set) and there is a
			<classname>ByteArrayMultipartEditor</classname> which converts files to byte
			arrays. They function just as the <classname>CustomDateEditor</classname>
			does.
      </para>
      <para>
			So, to be able to upload files using a (HTML) form, declare the resolver,
			a url mapping to a controller that will process the bean, and the controller
			itself.
	  </para>
	  <programlisting><![CDATA[<beans>
	<!-- lets use the Commons-based implementation of the MultipartResolver interface -->
    <bean id="multipartResolver"
        class="org.springframework.web.multipart.commons.CommonsMultipartResolver"/>

    <bean id="urlMapping" class="org.springframework.web.servlet.handler.SimpleUrlHandlerMapping">
        <property name="mappings">
            <value>
                /upload.form=fileUploadController
            </value>
        </property>
    </bean>

    <bean id="fileUploadController" class="examples.FileUploadController">
        <property name="commandClass" value="examples.FileUploadBean"/>
        <property name="formView" value="fileuploadform"/>
        <property name="successView" value="confirmation"/>
    </bean>

</beans>]]></programlisting>
      <para>
			After that, create the controller and the actual class to hold the file property.
	  </para>
	  <programlisting><![CDATA[public class FileUploadController extends SimpleFormController {

    protected ModelAndView onSubmit(
        HttpServletRequest request,
        HttpServletResponse response,
        Object command,
        BindException errors)
        throws ServletException, IOException {

        // cast the bean
        FileUploadBean bean = (FileUploadBean) command;

        // let's see if there's content there
        byte[] file = bean.getFile();
        if (file == null) {
            // hmm, that's strange, the user did not upload anything
        }

        // well, let's do nothing with the bean for now and return:
        return super.onSubmit(request, response, command, errors);
    }

    protected void initBinder(HttpServletRequest request, ServletRequestDataBinder binder)
        throws ServletException {
        // to actually be able to convert Multipart instance to byte[]
        // we have to register a custom editor
        binder.registerCustomEditor(byte[].class, new ByteArrayMultipartFileEditor());
        // now Spring knows how to handle multipart object and convert them
    }

}

public class FileUploadBean {

    private byte[] file;

    public void setFile(byte[] file) {
        this.file = file;
    }

    public byte[] getFile() {
        return file;
    }
}]]></programlisting>
	  <para>
			As you can see, the <classname>FileUploadBean</classname> has a property typed
			<literal>byte[]</literal> that holds the file. The controller registers
			a custom editor to let Spring know how to actually convert the multipart
			objects the resolver has found to properties specified by the bean. In
			this example, nothing is done with the <literal>byte[]</literal>
			property of the bean itself, but in practice you can do whatever you
			want (save it in a database, mail it to somebody, etc).
      </para>
      <para>
			An equivalent example in which a file is bound straight to a String-typed
			property on a (form backing) object might look like this:
      </para>
      <programlisting><![CDATA[public class FileUploadController extends SimpleFormController {

    protected ModelAndView onSubmit(
        HttpServletRequest request,
        HttpServletResponse response,
        Object command,
        BindException errors)
        throws ServletException, IOException {

        // cast the bean
        FileUploadBean bean = (FileUploadBean) command;

        // let's see if there's content there
        String file = bean.getFile();
        if (file == null) {
            // hmm, that's strange, the user did not upload anything
        }

        // well, let's do nothing with the bean for now and return:
        return super.onSubmit(request, response, command, errors);
    }

    protected void initBinder(HttpServletRequest request, ServletRequestDataBinder binder)
        throws ServletException {
        // to actually be able to convert Multipart instance to a String
        // we have to register a custom editor
        binder.registerCustomEditor(String.class, new StringMultipartFileEditor());
        // now Spring knows how to handle multipart object and convert them
    }

}

public class FileUploadBean {

    private String file;

    public void setFile(String file) {
        this.file = file;
    }

    public String getFile() {
        return file;
    }
}]]></programlisting>
        <para>
            Of course, this last example only makes (logical) sense in the context of uploading
            a plain text file (it wouldn't work so well in the case of uploading an image file).
        </para>
        <para>
            The third (and final) option is where one binds directly to a 
            <interfacename>MultipartFile</interfacename> property declared on the
            (form backing) object's class. In this case one does not need to register any
            custom <interfacename>PropertyEditor</interfacename> because there is no
            type conversion to be performed.
        </para>
      <programlisting><![CDATA[public class FileUploadController extends SimpleFormController {

    protected ModelAndView onSubmit(
        HttpServletRequest request,
        HttpServletResponse response,
        Object command,
        BindException errors)
        throws ServletException, IOException {

        // cast the bean
        FileUploadBean bean = (FileUploadBean) command;

        // let's see if there's content there
        MultipartFile file = bean.getFile();
        if (file == null) {
            // hmm, that's strange, the user did not upload anything
        }

        // well, let's do nothing with the bean for now and return:
        return super.onSubmit(request, response, command, errors);
    }
}

public class FileUploadBean {

    private MultipartFile file;

    public void setFile(MultipartFile file) {
        this.file = file;
    }

    public MultipartFile getFile() {
        return file;
    }
}]]></programlisting>
    </section>
  </section>

  <sect1 id="mvc-formtaglib">
    <title>Using Spring's form tag library</title>

    <para>As of version 2.0, Spring provides a comprehensive set of databinding-aware tags for handling form elements
    when using JSP and Spring MVC. Each tag provides support for the full set of attributes as specified by W3C,
    making the tags familiar to use. The tag-generated HTML is HTML 4.01/XHTML 1.0 compliant.</para>

    <para>Unlike other form/input tag libraries, Spring's form tag library is integrated with Spring MVC, giving
    the tags access to the command object and reference data your controller deals with. As you will see from the
    following examples, the form tags make JSPs easier to develop, read and maintain. </para>

  <sect2 id="mvc-formtaglib-configuration">
    <title><literal>Configuration</literal></title>
    <para>
        The form tag library comes bundled in <literal>spring.jar</literal>. The library descriptor is called
        <literal>spring-form.tld</literal>.</para>
    <para>To use the tags from this library, add the following directive to top of your JSP page:
    <programlisting>&lt;@ taglib prefix="form" uri="http://www.springframework.org/tags/form" %&gt;</programlisting>
    where <literal>form</literal> is the tag name prefix you want to use for the tags from this library.</para>

  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="mvc-formtaglib-formtag">
    <title>The <literal>form</literal> tag</title>
    <para>
        This tag renders an HTML 'form' tag and exposes a binding path to inner tags for binding. It puts the
        command object in the <literal>PageContext</literal> so that the command object can be accessed by inner tags.
        All the other tags in this library are nested tags of the <literal>form</literal> tag.
    </para>
    <para>
        Let's assume we have a domain object called <literal>User</literal>. It is a JavaBean with properties such as
        <literal>firstName</literal> and <literal>lastName</literal>. We use it as the form backing object of our
        <literal>FormController</literal> which returns <literal>form.jsp</literal>. Below is an example of what
        <literal>form.jsp</literal> would look like:
    </para>

    <programlisting><![CDATA[<form:form>
    <table>
        <tr>
            <td>First Name:</td>
            <td><form:input path="firstName" /></td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
            <td>Last Name:</td>
            <td><form:input path="lastName" /></td>
        </tr>
    </table>
</form:form>]]></programlisting>
    <para>
        The <literal>firstName</literal> and <literal>lastName</literal> values are retrieved from the command object
        placed in the <literal>PageContext</literal> by the page controller. Scroll on to see more complex examples
        of how inner tags are used with the <literal>form</literal> tag.
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="mvc-formtaglib-inputtag">
    <title>The <literal>input</literal> tag</title>
    <para>This tag renders an HTML 'input' tag with type 'text' using the bound value. For an example of this tag,
     see <xref linkend="mvc-formtaglib-formtag" />.</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="mvc-formtaglib-checkboxtag">
    <title>The <literal>checkbox</literal> tag</title>
      <para>This tag renders an HTML 'input' tag with type 'checkbox'.</para>
      <para>Let's assume that our <literal>User</literal> has preferences such as newsletter subscription
      and a list of hobbies. Below is an example of the <literal>Preferences</literal> class:</para>
  </sect2>      

   <programlisting><![CDATA[public class Preferences {

    private boolean receiveNewsletter;

    private String[] interests;

    private String favouriteWord;

    public boolean isReceiveNewsletter() {
        return receiveNewsletter;
    }

    public void setReceiveNewsletter(boolean receiveNewsletter) {
        this.receiveNewsletter = receiveNewsletter;
    }

    public String[] getInterests() {
        return interests;
    }

    public void setInterests(String[] interests) {
        this.interests = interests;
    }

    public String getFavouriteWord() {
        return favouriteWord;
    }

    public void setFavouriteWord(String favouriteWord) {
        this.favouriteWord = favouriteWord;
    }

}]]></programlisting>

    <para>The <literal>form.jsp</literal> would look like this:</para>

    <programlisting><![CDATA[<form:form>
    <table>
        <tr>
            <td>Subscribe to newsletter?:</td>
            <!-- Approach 1: Property is of type java.lang.Boolean -->
            <td><form:checkbox path="preferences.receiveNewsletter"/></td>
            <td></td>
        </tr>

        <tr>
            <td>Interests:</td>
            <td>
                <!-- Approach 2: Property is of an array or of type java.util.Collection -->
                Quidditch: <form:checkbox path="preferences.interests" value="Quidditch"/>
                Herbology: <form:checkbox path="preferences.interests" value="Herbology"/>
                Defence Against the Dark Arts: <form:checkbox path="preferences.interests" value="Defence Against the Dark Arts"/>
            </td>
            <td></td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
            <td>Favourite Word:</td>
            <td>
                <!-- Approach 3: Property is of type java.lang.Object -->
                Magic: <form:checkbox path="preferences.favouriteWord" value="Magic"/>
            </td>
            <td></td>
        </tr>
    </table>
</form:form>]]></programlisting>

      <para>There are 3 approaches to the <literal>checkbox</literal> tag which should meet all your checkbox needs.

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>Approach One  -  When the bound value is of type <literal>java.lang.Boolean</literal>,
            the <literal>input(checkbox)</literal> is marked as 'checked' if the bound value is
            <literal>true</literal>. The <literal>value</literal> attribute corresponds to the
            resolved value of the <literal>setValue(Object)</literal> value property.</listitem>

            <listitem>Approach Two - When the bound value is of type <literal>array</literal> or
            <literal>java.util.Collection</literal>, the <literal>input(checkbox)</literal> is marked as 'checked'
            if the configured <literal>setValue(Object)</literal> value is present in the bound
            <literal>Collection</literal>.</listitem>

            <listitem>Approach Three - For any other bound value type, the <literal>input(checkbox)</literal>
            is marked as 'checked' if the the configured <literal>setValue(Object)</literal> is equal to the
            bound value.</listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
      </para>

  <sect2 id="mvc-formtaglib-radiobuttontag">
    <title>The <literal>radiobutton</literal> tag</title>
    <para>This tag renders an HTML 'input' tag with type 'radio'.</para>
    <para>A typical usage pattern will involved multiple tag instances bound to the same property but with different
    values.</para>

    <programlisting><![CDATA[<form:form>
    <table>
        <tr>
            <td>Sex:</td>
            <td>Male: <form:radiobutton path="sex" value="M"/> <br/>
                Female: <form:radiobutton path="sex" value="F"/> </td>
            <td></td>
        </tr>
    </table>
</form:form>]]></programlisting>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="mvc-formtaglib-passwordtag">
    <title>The <literal>password</literal> tag</title>
    <para>This tag renders an HTML 'input' tag with type 'password' using the bound value.</para>

    <programlisting><![CDATA[<form:form>
    <table>
        <tr>
            <td>Password:</td>
            <td>
                <form:password path="password" />
            </td>
        </tr>
    </table>
</form:form>]]></programlisting>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="mvc-formtaglib-selecttag">
    <title>The <literal>select</literal> tag</title>
    <para>This tag renders an HTML 'select' element. It supports databinding to the selected option. It
    supports the use of nested <literal>option</literal> and <literal>options</literal> tags.</para>
    <para>Let's assume a <literal>User</literal> has a list of skills.</para>

    <programlisting><![CDATA[<form:form>
    <table>
    <tr>
        <td>Skills:</td>
        <td><form:select path="skills" items="${skills}"/></td>
        <td></td>
    </tr>
    </table>
</form:form>]]></programlisting>

    <para>If the <literal>User's</literal> skill was in Herbology, the HTML source of the 'Skills'
    row would look like this:</para>

    <programlisting><![CDATA[<tr>
    <td>Skills:</td>
    <td><select name="skills" multiple="true">
        <option value="Potions">Potions</option>
        <option value="Herbology" selected="true">Herbology</option>
        <option value="Quidditch">Quidditch</option></select></td>
    <td></td>
</tr>]]></programlisting>

  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="mvc-formtaglib-optiontag">
    <title>The <literal>option</literal> tag</title>
    <para>This tag renders an HTML 'option'. It sets 'selected' as appropriate based on bound value.</para>

    <programlisting><![CDATA[<form:form>
    <table>
        <tr>
            <td>House:</td>
            <td>
                <form:select path="house">
                    <form:option value="Gryffindor"/>
                    <form:option value="Hufflepuff"/>
                    <form:option value="Ravenclaw"/>
                    <form:option value="Slytherin"/>
                </form:select>
            </td>
        </tr>
    </table>
</form:form>]]></programlisting>

    <para>If the <literal>User's</literal> house was in Gryffindor, the HTML source of the 'House'
    row would look like this:</para>

    <programlisting><![CDATA[<tr>
    <td>House:</td>
    <td>
        <select name="house">
            <option value="Gryffindor" selected="true">Gryffindor</option>
            <option value="Hufflepuff">Hufflepuff</option>
            <option value="Ravenclaw">Ravenclaw</option>
            <option value="Slytherin">Slytherin</option>
        </select>
    </td>
 </tr>]]></programlisting>

  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="mvc-formtaglib-optionstag">
    <title>The <literal>options</literal> tag</title>
    <para>This tag renders a list of HTML 'option' tags. It sets 'selected' as appropriate based on bound value.</para>

    <programlisting><![CDATA[<form:form>
    <table>
        <tr>
            <td>Country:</td>
            <td>
                <form:select path="country">
                    <form:option value="-" label="--Please Select"/>
                    <form:options items="${countryList}" itemValue="code" itemLabel="name"/>
                </form:select>
            </td>
            <td></td>
        </tr>
    </table>
</form:form>]]></programlisting>

    <para>If the <literal>User's</literal> lived in the UK, the HTML source of the 'Country'
    row would look like this:</para>

    <programlisting><![CDATA[ <tr>
    <td>Country:</td>
    <tr>
        <td>Country:</td>
        <td>
            <select name="country">
                <option value="-">--Please Select</option>
                <option value="AT">Austria</option>
                <option value="UK" selected="true">United Kingdom</option>
                <option value="US">United States</option>
            </select>
        </td>
        <td></td>
    </tr>
    <td></td>
</tr>]]></programlisting>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="mvc-formtaglib-textAreatag">
    <title>The <literal>textarea</literal> tag</title>
    <para>This tag renders an HTML 'textarea'.</para>

    <programlisting><![CDATA[<form:form>
    <table>
        <tr>
            <td>Notes:</td>
            <td><form:textarea path="notes" rows="3" cols="20" /></td>
            <td><form:errors path="notes" /></td>
        </tr>
    </table>
</form:form>]]></programlisting>

  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="mvc-formtaglib-hiddeninputtag">
    <title>The <literal>hidden</literal> tag</title>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="mvc-formtaglib-errorstag">
    <title>The <literal>errors</literal> tag</title>
    <para>This tag renders an HTML 'input' tag with type 'hidden' using the bound value.</para>      
  </sect2>




  </sect1>


  <sect1 id="mvc-exceptionhandlers">
    <title>Handling exceptions</title>

    <para>Spring provides <literal>HandlerExceptionResolvers</literal> to ease
    the pain of unexpected exceptions occurring while your request is being
    handled by a controller which matched the request.
    <literal>HandlerExceptionResolvers</literal> somewhat resemble the
    exception mappings you can define in the web application descriptor
    <literal>web.xml</literal>. However, they provide a more flexible way to
    handle exceptions. They provide information about what handler was
    executing when the exception was thrown. Furthermore, a programmatic way
    of handling exception gives you many more options for how to respond
    appropriately before the request is forwarded to another URL (the same end
    result as when using the servlet specific exception mappings).</para>

    <para>Besides implementing the
    <literal>HandlerExceptionResolver</literal>, which is only a matter of
    implementing the <literal>resolveException(Exception, Handler)</literal>
    method and returning a <literal>ModelAndView</literal>, you may also use
    the <literal>SimpleMappingExceptionResolver</literal>. This resolver
    enables you to take the class name of any exception that might be thrown
    and map it to a view name. This is functionally equivalent to the
    exception mapping feature from the Servlet API, but it's also possible to
    implement more fine grained mappings of exceptions from different
    handlers.</para>
  </sect1>
</chapter>