<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="remoting">
  <title>Remoting and web services using Spring</title>
  
	<sect1>
		<title>Introduction</title>
		<para>
			Spring features integration classes for remoting support using various
			technologies. The remoting support eases the development of remote-enabled
			services, implemented by your usual (Spring) POJOs. Currently, Spring supports
			four remoting technologies:
			<itemizedlist spacing="compact">
				<listitem>
					<para>
						<emphasis>Remote Method Invocation (RMI)</emphasis>. Through the use
						of the <literal>RmiProxyFactoryBean</literal> and the
						<literal>RmiServiceExporter</literal> Spring supports both traditional
						RMI (with java.rmi.Remote interfaces and java.rmi.RemoteException) and
						transparent remoting via RMI invokers (with any Java interface).
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						<emphasis>Spring's HTTP invoker</emphasis>. Spring provides a special
						remoting strategy which allows for Java serialization via HTTP,
						supporting any Java interface (just like the RMI invoker). The corresponding
						support classes are <literal>HttpInvokerProxyFactoryBean</literal> and
						<literal>HttpInvokerServiceExporter</literal>.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						<emphasis>Hessian</emphasis>. By using the
						<literal>HessianProxyFactoryBean</literal>
						and the <literal>HessianServiceExporter</literal> you can transparently
						expose your services using the lightweight binary HTTP-based protocol
						provided by Caucho.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						<emphasis>Burlap</emphasis>. Burlap is Caucho's XML-based
						alternative for Hessian. Spring provides support classes such
						as <literal>BurlapProxyFactoryBean</literal> and 
						<literal>BurlapServiceExporter</literal>.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						<emphasis>JAX RPC</emphasis>. Spring provides remoting support
						for Web Services via JAX-RPC.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						<emphasis>JMS (TODO)</emphasis>.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</para>
		<para>
			While discussing the remoting capabilities of Spring, we'll use the following domain 
			model and corresponding services:
			<programlisting><![CDATA[
// Account domain object
public class Account implements Serializable{
  private String name;

  public String getName();
  public void setName(String name) {
    this.name = name;
  }
}
			]]></programlisting>
			<programlisting><![CDATA[
// Account service
public interface AccountService {

  public void insertAccount(Account acc);
  
  public List getAccounts(String name);
}
			]]></programlisting>
			<programlisting><![CDATA[
// Remote Account service
public interface RemoteAccountService extends Remote {

  public void insertAccount(Account acc) throws RemoteException;
  
  public List getAccounts(String name) throws RemoteException;
}
			]]></programlisting>
			<programlisting><![CDATA[
// ... and corresponding implement doing nothing at the moment
public class AccountServiceImpl implements AccountService {

  public void insertAccount(Account acc) {
    // do something
  }
  
  public List getAccounts(String name) {
    // do something
  }
}
			]]></programlisting>
		</para>
		<para>
			We will start exposing the service to a remote client by using RMI and 
			talk a bit about the drawbacks of using RMI. We'll then continue to show
			an example for Hessian.
		</para>		
	</sect1>	
	<sect1>
		<title>Exposing services using RMI</title>
		<para>
			Using Spring's support for RMI, you can transparently expose your services through
			the RMI infrastructure. After having this set up, you basically have a configuration
			similar to remote EJBs, except for the fact that there is no standard support for
			security context propagation or remote transaction propagation. Spring does provide
			hooks for such additional invocation context when using the RMI invoker, so you can
			for example plug in security frameworks or custom security credentials here.
		</para>
		<sect2>
			<title>Exporting the service using the <literal>RmiServiceExporter</literal></title>
			<para>
				Using the <literal>RmiServiceExporter</literal>, we can expose the interface
				of our AccountService object as RMI object. The interface can be accessed by using
				<literal>RmiProxyFactoryBean</literal>, or via plain RMI in case of a traditional
				RMI service. The <literal>RmiServiceExporter</literal> explicitly supports the
				exposing of any non-RMI services via RMI invokers.
			</para>
			<para>
				Of course, we first have to set up our service in the Spring BeanFactory:
				<programlisting><![CDATA[
<bean id="accountService" class="example.AccountServiceImpl">
    <!-- any additional properties, maybe a DAO? -->
</bean>
				]]></programlisting>
			</para>
			<para>
				Next we'll have to expose our service using the <literal>RmiServiceExporter</literal>:
				<programlisting><![CDATA[
<bean class="org.springframework.remoting.rmi.RmiServiceExporter">
	<!-- does not necessarily have to be the same name as the bean to be exported -->
	<property name="serviceName" value="AccountService"/>
	<property name="service" ref="accountService"/>
	<property name="serviceInterface" value="example.AccountService"/>
	<!-- defaults to 1099 -->
	<property name="registryPort" value="1199"/>
</bean>
				]]></programlisting>
				As you can see, we're overriding the port for the RMI registry. Often,
				your application server also maintains an RMI registry and it is wise
				to not interfere with that one.
				Furthermore, the service name is used to bind the service under. So right now,
				the service will be bound at <literal>rmi://HOST:1199/AccountService</literal>.				
				We'll use the URL later on to link in the service at the client side.
			</para>
			<para>
				<emphasis>Note: We've left out one property, i.e. the <literal>servicePort</literal>
					property, which is 0 by default. This means an anonymous port will be used
					to communicate with the service. You can specify a different port if you like.</emphasis>
			</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2>
			<title>Linking in the service at the client</title>
			<para>
				Our client is a simple object using the AccountService to manage accounts:
				<programlisting><![CDATA[
public class SimpleObject {
  private AccountService accountService;
  public void setAccountService(AccountService accountService) {
    this.accountService = accountService;
  }
}
				]]></programlisting>				
			</para>
			<para>
				To link in the service on the client, we'll create a separate bean factory,
				containing the simple object and the service linking configuration bits:
				<programlisting><![CDATA[
<bean class="example.SimpleObject">
	<property name="accountService" ref="accountService"/>
</bean>

<bean id="accountService" class="org.springframework.remoting.rmi.RmiProxyFactoryBean">
	<property name="serviceUrl" value="rmi://HOST:1199/AccountService"/>
	<property name="serviceInterface" value="example.AccountService"/>
</bean>
				]]></programlisting>
				That's all we need to do to support the remote account service on the client.
				Spring will transparently create an invoker and remotely enable the account
				service through the RmiServiceExporter. At the client we're linking it in using
				the RmiProxyFactoryBean.
			</para>
		</sect2>				
	</sect1>
	<sect1>
		<title>Using Hessian or Burlap to remotely call services via HTTP</title>
		<para>
			Hessian offers a binary HTTP-based remoting protocol. It's created by
			Caucho and more information about Hessian itself can be found 
			at <ulink url="http://www.caucho.com"/>.			
		</para>
		<sect2>
			<title>Wiring up the DispatcherServlet for Hessian</title>
			<para>
				Hessian communicates via HTTP and does so using a custom servlet.
				Using Spring's DispatcherServlet principles, you can easily 
				wire up such a servlet exposing your services. First we'll have to
				create a new servlet in your application (this an excerpt from
				<literal>web.xml</literal>):
				<programlisting><![CDATA[
<servlet>
	<servlet-name>remoting</servlet-name>
	<servlet-class>org.springframework.web.servlet.DispatcherServlet</servlet-class>
	<load-on-startup>1</load-on-startup>
</servlet>

<servlet-mapping>
	<servlet-name>remoting</servlet-name>
	<url-pattern>/remoting/*</url-pattern>
</servlet-mapping>
				]]></programlisting>
			</para>
			<para>
				You're probably familiar with Spring's DispatcherServlet principles and if so,
				you know that now you'll have to create an application context named
				<literal>remoting-servlet.xml</literal> (after the name of your servlet) in
				the <literal>WEB-INF</literal> directory. The application context will be used
				in the next section.
			</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2>
			<title>Exposing your beans by using the HessianServiceExporter</title>
			<para>
				In the newly created application context called <literal>remoting-servlet.xml</literal>,
				we'll create a HessianServiceExporter exporting your services:
				<programlisting><![CDATA[
<bean id="accountService" class="example.AccountServiceImpl">
  <!-- any additional properties, maybe a DAO? -->
</bean>

<bean name="/AccountService" class="org.springframework.remoting.caucho.HessianServiceExporter">
  <property name="service" ref="accountService"/>
  <property name="serviceInterface" value="example.AccountService"/>
</bean>
				]]></programlisting>
				Now we're ready to link in the service at the client. No explicit handler mapping
				is specified, mapping request URLs onto services, so BeanNameUrlHandlerMapping
				will be used: hence, the service will be exported at the URL indicated through
				its bean name: <literal>http://HOST:8080/remoting/AccountService</literal>.
			</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2>
			<title>Linking in the service on the client</title>
			<para>
				Using the <literal>HessianProxyFactoryBean</literal> we can link in the service
				at the client. The same principles apply as with the RMI example. We'll create
				a separate bean factory or application context and mention the following beans
				where the SimpleObject is using the AccountService to manage accounts:
				<programlisting><![CDATA[
<bean class="example.SimpleObject">
  <property name="accountService" ref="accountService"/>
</bean>

<bean id="accountService" class="org.springframework.remoting.caucho.HessianProxyFactoryBean">
	<property name="serviceUrl" value="http://remotehost:8080/AccountService"/>
	<property name="serviceInterface" value="example.AccountService"/>
</bean>
				]]></programlisting>
				That's all there is to it.
			</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2>
			<title>Using Burlap</title>
			<para>
				We won't discuss Burlap, the XML-based equivalent of Hessian, in detail here,
				since it is configured and set up in exactly the same way as the Hessian
				variant explained above. Just replace the word <literal>Hessian</literal>
				with <literal>Burlap</literal> and you're all set to go.
			</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2>
			<title>Applying HTTP basic authentication to a service exposed through Hessian or Burlap</title>
			<para>
				One of the advantages of Hessian and Burlap is that we can easily apply HTTP basic
				authentication, because both protocols are HTTP-based. Your normal HTTP server security
				mechanism can easily be applied through using the <literal>web.xml</literal> security
				features, for example. Usually, you don't use per-user security credentials here, but
				rather shared credentials defined at the Hessian/BurlapProxyFactoryBean level
				(similar to a JDBC DataSource).
			</para>
			<para>
				<programlisting><![CDATA[
<bean class="org.springframework.web.servlet.handler.BeanNameUrlHandlerMapping">
	<property name="interceptors">
		<list>
			<ref bean="authorizationInterceptor"/>
		</list>
	</property>
</bean>

<bean id="authorizationInterceptor" 
	class="org.springframework.web.servlet.handler.UserRoleAuthorizationInterceptor">
	<property name="authorizedRoles">
		<list>
			<value>administrator</value>
			<value>operator</value>
		</list>
	</property>	
</bean>
				]]></programlisting>
			</para>
			<para>
				This an example where we explicitly mention the BeanNameUrlHandlerMapping
				and set an interceptor allowing only administrators and operators to call
				the beans mentioned in this application context.
			</para>
			<para>
				<emphasis>
					Note: Of course, this example doesn't show a flexible kind of security
					infrastructure. For more options as far as security is concerned,
					have a look at the Acegi Security System for Spring, to be found at
					<ulink url="http://acegisecurity.sourceforge.net"/>.
				</emphasis>
			</para>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>
	
	<sect1>
		<title>Exposing services using HTTP invokers</title>
		<para>
			As opposed to Burlap and Hessian, which are both lightweight protocols using their
			own slim serialization mechanisms, Spring Http invokers use the standard
			Java serialization mechanism to expose services through HTTP. This has a huge
			advantage if your arguments and return types are complex types that cannot be
			serialized using the serialization mechanisms Hessian and Burlap use (refer to the
			next section for more considerations when choosing a remoting technology).
		</para>
		<para>
			Under the hood, Spring uses either the standard facilities provided by J2SE to
			perform HTTP calls or Commons HttpClient. Use the latter if you need more advanced
			and easy-to-use functionality. Refer to 
			<ulink url="http://jakarta.apache.org/commons/httpclient">jakarta.apache.org/commons/httpclient</ulink>
			for more info.
		</para>
		<sect2>
			<title>Exposing the service object</title>
			<para>
				Setting up the HTTP invoker infrastructure for a service objects much resembles
				the way you would do using Hessian or Burlap. Just as Hessian support provides
				the <literal>HessianServiceExporter</literal>, Spring Http invoker support provides
				the so-called <literal>org.springframework.remoting.httpinvoker.HttpInvokerServiceExporter</literal>.
				To expose the <literal>AccountService</literal> (mentioned above), the following
				configuration needs to be in place:
<programlisting><![CDATA[
<bean name="/AccountService" class="org.sprfr.remoting.httpinvoker.HttpInvokerServiceExporter">
  <property name="service" ref="accountService"/>
  <property name="serviceInterface" value="example.AccountService"/>
</bean>
]]></programlisting>
			</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2>
			<title>Linking in the service at the client</title>
			<para>
				Again, linking in the service from the client much resembles the way you would
				do it when using Hessian or Burlap. Using a proxy, Spring will be able to
				translate your calls to HTTP POST requests to the URL pointing to the exported
				service.
<programlisting><![CDATA[
<bean id="httpInvokerProxy" class="org.sprfr.remoting.httpinvoker.HttpInvokerProxyFactoryBean">
  <property name="serviceUrl" value="http://remotehost:8080/AccountService"/>
  <property name="serviceInterface" value="example.AccountService"/>
</bean>
]]></programlisting>
			</para>
			<para>
				As mentioned before, you can choose what HTTP client you want to use.
				By default, the HttpInvokerProxy uses the J2SE HTTP functionality, but
				you can also use the Commons HttpClient by setting the <literal>httpInvokerRequestExecutor</literal> property:
<programlisting><![CDATA[
<property name="httpInvokerRequestExecutor">
	<bean class="org.springframework.remoting.httpinvoker.CommonsHttpInvokerRequestExecutor"/>
</property>
]]></programlisting>
			</para>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>
	
	<sect1>
		<title>Web Services</title>
		<para>
			Spring has support for:
			<itemizedlist spacing="compact">
				<listitem>Exposing services using JAX-RPC</listitem>
				<listitem>Accessing Web Services</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</para>
        <para>
            Next to the support listed above, you can also expose your web services using
            XFire <ulink url="http://xfire.codehaus.org">xfire.codehaus.org</ulink>.
            XFire is a ligthweight SOAP library, currently in development at Codehaus.
        </para>
		<sect2>
			<title>Exposing services using JAX-RPC</title>
			<para>
				Spring has a convenience base class for JAX-RPC servlet endpoint implementations -
				<literal>ServletEndpointSupport</literal>. To expose our AccountService we extend Spring's ServletEndpointSupport class
				and implement our business logic here, usually delegating the call to the business layer.
<programlisting><![CDATA[
/**
 * JAX-RPC compliant RemoteAccountService implementation that simply delegates
 * to the AccountService implementation in the root web application context.
 *
 * This wrapper class is necessary because JAX-RPC requires working with
 * RMI interfaces. If an existing service needs to be exported, a wrapper that
 * extends ServletEndpointSupport for simple application context access is
 * the simplest JAX-RPC compliant way.
 *
 * This is the class registered with the server-side JAX-RPC implementation.
 * In the case of Axis, this happens in "server-config.wsdd" respectively via
 * deployment calls. The Web Service tool manages the life-cycle of instances
 * of this class: A Spring application context can just be accessed here.
 */
public class AccountServiceEndpoint extends ServletEndpointSupport implements RemoteAccountService {
    
    private AccountService biz;
	
    protected void onInit() {
        this.biz = (AccountService) getWebApplicationContext().getBean("accountService");
    }

    public void insertAccount(Account acc) throws RemoteException {
        biz.insertAccount(acc);
    }
  
    public Account[] getAccounts(String name) throws RemoteException {
        return biz.getAccounts(name);
    }
  
}	
]]></programlisting>
				Our AccountServletEndpoint needs to run in the same web application as the Spring context to allow for access
				to Spring's facilities. In case of Axis, copy the AxisServlet definition into your web.xml, and set up
				the endpoint in "server-config.wsdd" (or use the deploy tool).
				See the sample application JPetStore where the OrderService is exposed as a Web Service using Axis.
			</para>
		</sect2>

		<sect2>
			<title>Accessing Web Services</title>
			<para>
				Spring has two factory beans to create web service proxies <literal>LocalJaxRpcServiceFactoryBean</literal> and
				<literal>JaxRpcPortProxyFactoryBean</literal>. The former can only return a JAX-RPC Service class for us to work with.
				The latter is the full fledged version that can return a proxy that implements our business service interface.
				In this example we use the later to create a proxy for the AccountService Endpoint we exposed in the previous paragraph.
				You will see that Spring has great support for Web Services requiring little coding efforts - most of the magic is done in
				the spring configuration file as usual:
<programlisting><![CDATA[
    <bean id="accountWebService" class="org.springframework.remoting.jaxrpc.JaxRpcPortProxyFactoryBean">
        <property name="serviceInterface">
            <value>example.RemoteAccountService</value>
        </property>
        <property name="wsdlDocumentUrl">
            <value>http://localhost:8080/account/services/accountService?WSDL</value>
        </property>
        <property name="namespaceUri">
            <value>http://localhost:8080/account/services/accountService</value>
        </property>
        <property name="serviceName">
            <value>AccountService</value>
        </property>
        <property name="portName">
            <value>AccountPort</value>
        </property>
    </bean>
]]></programlisting>
				Where <literal>serviceInterface</literal> is our remote business interface the clients will use.
				<literal>wsdlDocumentUrl</literal> is the URL for the WSDL file. Spring needs this a startup time to create the JAX-RPC Service.
				<literal>namespaceUri</literal> corresponds to the targetNamespace in the .wsdl file.
				<literal>serviceName</literal> corresponds to the serivce name in the .wsdl file.
				<literal>portName</literal> corresponds to the port name in the .wsdl file.
			</para>
			<para>
				Accessing the Web Service is now very easy as we have a bean factory for it that will expose it as <literal>RemoteAccountService</literal>
				interface. We can wire this up in Spring:
<programlisting><![CDATA[
    <bean id="client" class="example.AccountClientImpl">
        ...
        <property name="service" ref="accountWebService"/>
    </bean>
]]></programlisting>
				And from the client code we can access the Web Service just as if it was a normal class, except that it throws RemoteException.
<programlisting><![CDATA[
public class AccountClientImpl {

    private RemoteAccountService service;
    
    public void setService(RemoteAccountService service) {
        this.service = service;
    }
    
    public void foo() {
       try {
           service.insertAccount(...);
        } catch (RemoteException e) {
           // ouch
           ...
        }
     }
     
}
]]></programlisting>
			</para>
			<para>
				We can get rid of the checked RemoteException since Spring supports automatic conversion to its corresponding unchecked
				<literal>RemoteAccessException</literal>. This requires that we provide a non RMI interface also. Our configuration is now:
<programlisting><![CDATA[
    <bean id="accountWebService" class="org.springframework.remoting.jaxrpc.JaxRpcPortProxyFactoryBean">
        <property name="serviceInterface">
            <value>example.AccountService</value>
        </property>
        <property name="portInterface">
            <value>example.RemoteAccountService</value>
        </property>
        ...
    </bean>
]]></programlisting>
				Where <literal>serviceInterface</literal> is changed to our non RMI interface. Our RMI interface is now defined using the property
				<literal>portInterface</literal>. Our client code can now avoid handling <literal>java.rmi.RemoteException</literal>:
<programlisting><![CDATA[
public class AccountClientImpl {

    private AccountService service;
    
    public void setService(AccountService service) {
        this.service = service;
    }
    
    public void foo() {
        service.insertAccount(...);
     }
     
}
]]></programlisting>
    		</para>
		</sect2>
		
		<sect2>
			<title>Register Bean Mappings</title>
			<para>
				To transfer complex objects over the wire such as Account we must register bean mappings on the client side.
				<note>
					<para>
						On the server side using Axis registering bean mappings is usually done in server-config.wsdd.
					</para>						
				</note>
				We will use Axis to register bean mappings on the client side. To do this we need to subclass Spring Bean factory and
				register the bean mappings programmatic:
<programlisting><![CDATA[
public class AxisPortProxyFactoryBean extends JaxRpcPortProxyFactoryBean {

	protected void postProcessJaxRpcService(Service service) {
		TypeMappingRegistry registry = service.getTypeMappingRegistry();
		TypeMapping mapping = registry.createTypeMapping();
		registerBeanMapping(mapping, Account.class, "Account");
		registry.register("http://schemas.xmlsoap.org/soap/encoding/", mapping);
	}

	protected void registerBeanMapping(TypeMapping mapping, Class type, String name) {
		QName qName = new QName("http://localhost:8080/account/services/accountService", name);
		mapping.register(type, qName,
		    new BeanSerializerFactory(type, qName),
		    new BeanDeserializerFactory(type, qName));
	}

}
]]></programlisting>
			</para>
		</sect2>

		<sect2>
			<title>Registering our own Handler</title>
			<para>
				In this section we will register our own <literal>javax.rpc.xml.handler.Handler</literal> to the Web Service Proxy
				where we can do custom code before the SOAP message is sent over the wire.
				The <literal>javax.rpc.xml.handler.Handler</literal> is a callback interface. There is a convenience base class provided
				in jaxrpc.jar -	<literal>javax.rpc.xml.handler.GenericHandler</literal> that we will extend:
<programlisting><![CDATA[
public class AccountHandler extends GenericHandler {

    public QName[] getHeaders() {
        return null;
    }

    public boolean handleRequest(MessageContext context) {
        SOAPMessageContext smc = (SOAPMessageContext) context;
        SOAPMessage msg = smc.getMessage();

        try {
            SOAPEnvelope envelope = msg.getSOAPPart().getEnvelope();
            SOAPHeader header = envelope.getHeader();
            ...
		
        } catch (SOAPException e) {
            throw new JAXRPCException(e);
        }

        return true;
    }

}
]]></programlisting>
			What we need to do now is to register our AccountHandler to JAX-RPC Service so it would invoke <literal>handleRequest</literal>
			before the message is sent over the wire. Spring has at this time of writing no declarative support for registering handlers.
			So we must use the programmatic approach. However Spring has made it very easy for us to do this as we can extend its bean factory
			and override its <literal>postProcessJaxRpcService</literal> method that is designed for this: 
<programlisting><![CDATA[
public class AccountHandlerJaxRpcPortProxyFactoryBean extends JaxRpcPortProxyFactoryBean {

    protected void postProcessJaxRpcService(Service service) {
        QName port = new QName(this.getNamespaceUri(), this.getPortName());
        List list = service.getHandlerRegistry().getHandlerChain(port);
        list.add(new HandlerInfo(AccountHandler.class, null, null));

        logger.info("Registered JAX-RPC Handler [" + AccountHandler.class.getName() + "] on port " + port);
    }

}
]]></programlisting>
			And the last thing we must remember to do is to change the Spring configuration to use our factory bean:
<programlisting><![CDATA[
    <bean id="accountWebService" class="example.AccountHandlerJaxRpcPortProxyFactoryBean">
        ...
    </bean>    
]]></programlisting>
			</para>
		</sect2>

        <sect2>
            <title>Exposing web services using XFire</title>
            <para>
                XFire is a lightweight SOAP library, hosted by Codehaus. At the time of writing (March 2005), XFire
                is still in development. Although Spring support is stable, lots of features should be added in the future.
                Exposing XFire is done using an XFire context that shipping with XFire itself in combination with a
                RemoteExporter-style bean you have to add to your WebApplicationContext.
            </para>
            <para>
                As with all methods that allow you to expose service, you have to create a DispatcherServlet with
                a corresponding WebApplicationContext containing the services you will be exposing:
                <programlisting><![CDATA[
<servlet>
  <servlet-name>xfire</servlet-name>
  <servlet-class>
    org.springframework.web.servlet.DispatcherServlet
  </servlet-class>
</servlet>
                ]]></programlisting>
            </para>
            <para>
                You also have to link in the XFire configuration. This is done by adding a context file to the
                <literal>contextConfigLocations</literal> context parameter picked up by the ContextLoaderListener
                (or Servlet for that matter). The configuration file is located in the XFire jar and should of course
                be placed on the classpath of your application archive.
                <programlisting><![CDATA[
<context-param>
  <param-name>contextConfigLocation</param-name>
  <param-value>
    classpath:org/codehaus/xfire/spring/xfire.xml
  </param-value>
</context-param>

<listener>
  <listener-class>
    org.springframework.web.context.ContextLoaderListener
  </listener-class>
</listener>
                ]]></programlisting>
            </para>

            <para>
              After you added a servlet mapping (mapping /* to the XFire servlet declared above) you only have to add
              one extra bean to expose the service using XFire. Add for example the following you <literal>xfire-servlet.xml</literal>:
              <programlisting><![CDATA[
<beans>
  <bean name="/Echo" class="org.codehaus.xfire.spring.XFireExporter">
    <property name="service" ref="echo">
    <property name="serviceInterface" value="org.codehaus.xfire.spring.Echo"/>
    <property name="serviceBuilder" ref="xfire.serviceBuilder"/>
    <!-- the XFire bean is wired up in the xfire.xml file you've linked in earlier
    <property name="xfire" ref="xfire"/>
  </bean>

  <bean id="echo" class="org.codehaus.xfire.spring.EchoImpl"/>
</beans>
]]></programlisting>
            </para>
            <para>
              XFire handles the rest. It introspects your service interface and generates a WSDL from it.
              Parts of this documentation have been taken from the XFire site. For more detailed information on XFire
              Spring integration, have a look at the <ulink url="http://docs.codehaus.org/display/XFIRE/Spring">docs.codehaus.org/display/XFIRE/Spring</ulink>.
            </para>
        </sect2>

	</sect1>


	<sect1>
        <title>Auto-detection is not implemented for remote interfaces</title>
        <para>
            The main reason why auto-detection of implemented interfaces does not occur for
            remote interfaces is to avoid opening too many doors to remote callers. The target
            object might implement internal callback interfaces like InitializingBean or
            DisposableBean which one would not want to expose to callers.
        </para>
        <para>
            Offering a proxy with all interfaces implemented by the target usually does not
            matter in the local case. But when exporting a remote service, you should expose
            a specific service interface, with specific operations intended for remote usage.
            Besides internal callback interfaces, the target might implement multiple business
            interfaces, with just one of them intended for remote exposure. For these reasons,
            we <emphasis>require</emphasis> such a service interface to be specified.
        </para>
        <para>
            This is a trade-off between configuration convenience and the risk of accidental
            exposure of internal methods. Always specifying a service interface is not too much
            effort, and puts you on the safe side regarding controlled exposure of specific
            methods.
        </para>
    </sect1>

	<sect1>
		<title>Considerations when choosing a technology</title>
		<para>
			Each and every technology presented here has its drawbacks. You should carefully
			consider you needs, the services your exposing and the objects you'll be sending
			over the wire when choosing a technology.
		</para>
		<para>
			When using RMI, it's not possible to access the objects through the HTTP protocol,
			unless you're tunneling the RMI traffic. RMI is a fairly heavy-weight protocol
			in that it support full-object serialization which is important when using a
			complex data model that needs serialization over the wire. However, RMI-JRMP
			is tied to Java clients: It is a Java-to-Java remoting solution.
		</para>
		<para>
			Spring's HTTP invoker is a good choice if you need HTTP-based remoting but also
			rely on Java serialization. It shares the basic infrastructure with RMI invokers,
			just using HTTP as transport. Note that HTTP invokers are not only limited to
			Java-to-Java remoting but also to Spring on both the client and server side.
			(The latter also applies to Spring's RMI invoker for non-RMI interfaces.)
		</para>
		<para>
			Hessian and/or Burlap might provide significant value when operating in a
			heterogeneous environment, because they explicitly allow for non-Java clients.
			However, non-Java support is still limited. Known problems include the serialization
			of Hibernate objects in combination with lazily initializing collections. If you
			have such a data model, consider using RMI or HTTP invokers instead of Hessian.
		</para>
		<para>
			JMS can be useful for providing clusters of services and allowing the JMS broker
      to take care of load balancing, discovery and auto-failover.
      By default Java serialization is used when using JMS remoting but
      the JMS provider could use a different mechanism for the wire formatting,
      such as XStream to allow servers to be implemented in other technologies.
		</para>
		<para>
			Last but not least, EJB has an advantage over RMI in that it supports standard
			role-based authentication and authorization and remote transaction propagation.
			It is possible to get RMI invokers or HTTP invokers to support security context
			propagation as well, although this is not provided by core Spring: There are
			just appropriate hooks for plugging in third-party or custom solutions here.
		</para>
	</sect1>
</chapter>
