<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<appendix id="xsd-config">
	<title>XML Schema-based configuration</title>
	<section>
		<title>Introduction</title>
		<para>This section of the reference documentation details the XML Schema based
    configuration that was introduced in Spring 2.0.</para>
		<sidebar>
			<title>DTD?</title>
			<para>Authoring Spring configuration files using the older DTD style
			is still totally supported.</para>
			<para>Nothing will break if you forego the use of the new XML Schema-based
			approach to authoring Spring XML configuration files. All that you lose
			out on is more succinct and clearer configuration... in the end all of the
			XML configuration, be it DTD- or Schema-based all boils down to the same
			object model in the container.</para>
		</sidebar>
		<para>The central motivation for moving to XML Schema based configuration files was
		to enable easier Spring (unsurprisingly). The <emphasis>'classic'</emphasis>
		<literal>&lt;bean/&gt;</literal>-based approach is good (and it still continues
		to be good), but it does suffer from being a tad generic.</para>
		<para>From the Spring IoC containers point of view, <emphasis>everything</emphasis>
		is a bean. Thats great news for the Spring IoC container, because if everything is
		a bean then everything can be treated the same. The same is not true for
		developers... the objects (or classes rather) that one defines in a Spring
		XML configuration file are not all generic, vanilla beans.</para>
		<para>Spring 2.0's new XML Schema-based configuration addresses this issue.
		The <literal>&lt;bean/&gt;</literal> element is still present, and if one
		wanted to one could continue to write the <emphasis>exact same</emphasis>
		style of Spring XML configuration using only <literal>&lt;bean/&gt;</literal>
		elements. The new XML Schema-based configuration does however result in
		Spring XML configuration files that are substantially clearer to read, and
		that allow one to express the intent of what a bean definition is.
		</para>
		<para>The examples included below will hopefully convince you that the inclusion
		of XML Schema support in Spring 2.0 was a good idea. The Spting team certainly
		thinks so, and the reception in the community has been encouraging; something that
		is not covered in this section (at least not right now) is the fact that this
		new configuration mechanism is totally customisable and extensible. This means
		that one can write one's own domain specific configuration that allows one
		to more succinctly express one's domain.</para>
	</section>
	<section id="xsd-config-body">
		<title>XML Schema-based configuration</title>
		<section id="xsd-config-body-referencing">
			<title>Referencing the schemas</title>
			<para>[TODO : explain how to locate and reference the correct schemas at the top of ones configuratio file]</para>
		</section>
		<section id="xsd-config-body-schemas-util">
			<title>The <literal>util</literal> schema</title>
			<para>[TODO : provide examples or links to examples (with screenshots)]</para>
		</section>
	</section>
	<section id="xsd-config-setup">
		<title>Setting up your IDE</title>
		<para>This final section documents the steps involved in setting up a number of
		popular Java IDEs to effect the easier editing of Spring's XML Schema-based
		configuration files.</para>
		<para>If your favourite Java IDE or editor is not included in the list of
		documented IDEs, then please do raise an issue (or ticket) on the Spring
		Framework
		<ulink linkend="http://opensource.atlassian.com/projects/spring/secure/Dashboard.jspa">JIRA</ulink>
		and the oversight <emphasis>may</emphasis> well be addressed in the next release.</para>
		<section id="xsd-config-setup-eclipse">
			<title>Setting up Eclipse</title>
			<para>[TODO :  document setting up Eclipse (with screenshots)]</para>
		</section>
		<section id="xsd-config-setup-idea">
			<title>Setting up IDEA</title>
			<para>[TODO :  document setting up IDEA (with screenshots)]</para>
		</section>
	</section>
</appendix>